hello everyone and welcome back to the
show today I am joined by Julian kin
senior researcher in the department of
Psychiatry at Amsterdam medical research
Professor kin's work is fascinating and
deeply important as he has developed
phenomenologically informed answers to a
number of questions in cognitive science
including time perception conceptual
thinking empathy Free Will Consciousness
and the self in doing so he has become a
leading intellectual in the world of 4E
cognitive science as he puts it
cognitive scientists once shared a
vision of Mind as a kind of logic engine
carrying out rule-based operations on
symbolic representations today this view
is rapidly being replaced by an
alternative vision of brain body and
world as dynamically interacting equal
Partners sharing the load in our
day-to-day problem solving Behavior
Professor kin's work has also been
highly impactful on my own thinking in
these domains so honestly I am really
really excited to speak to you today uh
Professor kinee Julian thank you so much
for joining me it's it's as I said it
really is a privilege thanks so much for
inviting me looking forward to our
discussion very much as am I and I think
uh you know I read I I've read some of
your papers multiple times and and I
adore them I think some of them are
absolute gems in in the foury sort of
lineage thank you and you sort of
proposed this notion of eological
inactive
cognition um now fory cogy inactive
cognition has a very rich history and
it's worthwhile unpicking what some of
these terms mean because I can imagine
people are going to get confused because
they're rather Niche terms at least they
can sound uh as so so it'd be good to
get maybe just some definitions off the
ground perhaps we could start with
autonomy versus heton
heteronomy yeah uh what does it mean to
be a kind of autonomous
being yeah so that is an excellent
starting point uh well autonomy is like
a a very rich concept with a long
history um but the way that it's used in
the context of philosophy of cognitive
science is by drawing on ideas about
biological autonomy so autonomy is like
a form of
self-organization that a living system
has when it is both self- producing so
that's basic to the idea of
self-organization that the the
organization is something that
emerges and so the structure the form
that the living system has is something
that's emergent but also that um that
that autonomous systems are able to uh
keep themselves
going um so maintain their
organization and and that requires them
to to be self- individuating in a
particular way so distinguishing
themselves from their
environment um so I think those are the
the two key features that we need to
have in view the self-
distinction uh self- production or self-
individuation as I call it sure I've
been uh I've been sort of perusing Evan
Thompson's 2007 mind in life which is
just cracking but also super long so I'm
working my way through it slowly and
here's a bit where he says well autonomy
it's it's sometimes quite tricky to say
when something is explicitly autonomous
rather than
heteronomous I think that's the right
way of saying it um do you subscribe to
that notion that this is kind of a
spectrum or there these can we cast
these sharp dividing
lines yeah so there's a there's a
technical discussion about whether autop
poesis is necessary and sufficient for
autonomy I think maybe that's what
you're thinking about so autop poesis is
this idea that the organization is
self-produced and and there's some
questions about well is that enough on
its own to to get autonomy right and and
Evan argues it isn't uh so you need and
so does AO dep Paulo you need this extra
condition of um adaptivity as they call
it Y in my work with Michael kof we uh
we connect that idea of adaptivity to to
active inference yes so we discussed
this in in the context of an issue
that's come up quite a few times on your
your podcast about uh to say about
Pebbles or yes swinging pendulums that
seem to behave as if they are minimizing
free
energy um but uh it still seems like uh
well if free energy principle is so
General as to apply to the behavior of
those kinds of physical systems how is
it going to be useful to use that uh the
mathematics of the free energy principle
to to understand uh life and M so
perhaps before we we get there it'd be
worthwhile just so people are aware what
does someone like Evan Thompson mean by
adaptivity yeah sorry so adaptivity is
uh is this ability of living systems to
um to regulate their encounters with the
environment it requires a sensitivity to
uh tendencies that can be sensed in the
environment where those Tendencies could
be um threatening to the precarious
organization of the of the living being
of the
agent so adaptivity is like moving
towards dynamical tendencies that are
going to sustain the organization of the
system and away from tendencies that are
are threatening are going to Le to uh
disintegration or collapse and this
sounds to me like there's got piece this
implies some necessary coupling with the
environment whereby to use active
inference terms you are there's some
conditional dependencies via Mark of
blanket let's say I mean that's
interesting because uh as I'm as you
know this vising contests with some of
the earlier formulations of autonomy um
so verel for example in 79 writes the
environmental elements intervening
between the effector and the sensory
service of uh surface of the organism is
irrelevant because the nervous system
can be redefined as a network of
neuronal interactions in terms of the
interactions of its component neurons
regardless of intervening elements so
that brings in this notion of
operational or organizational closure
perhaps it's worth explaining to the
audience why at least uh on first glance
that might seem like it uh engenders
some notion of
internalism yeah so certainly the the
way that farella defines autonomy in the
uh in that 1979 quote you just gave us
um would entail a very strong form of
internalism where the the environment is
just providing perturbations to the
autonomous organization of the living
system I don't think in the end that is
what verella intended but uh there there
are places where he certainly sounds
like uh it's it's a view where the the
world is kind of or the meaning that we
find in the world is something that's
projected by the living organism onto
the
environment can be read as a kind of
solipsism or idealism if uh without
without some careful handling sure
machana and verela had this metaphor of
the the submarine where yeah you're you
know you're underwater and and all that
you have in terms of access to the
external world is through the Periscope
and this is sounds very similar to some
of the things that we hear in active
inference quite a lot where there are
hidden causes out in the world and we
have to infer from our sensory States
what it is that are causing those
sensory States because we have no direct
or immediate
access uh to those hidden causes yeah
you know I think the quote that you just
read really fits with that view of uh of
life and or
me um but I think that uh at the same
time um we can think of the Markoff
blanket as coupling us to the
environment this was something that came
up in your discussion with
inis it separates us from our
surroundings if we think of the Markoff
blanket around the organism we can of
course talk about where to place the
Markoff blanket that's one of the things
that has also come up many times in your
discussions um but focusing on the the
Markoff blanket arounds the the
biologically autonomous
system um we can think of that as
separating or enforcing some kind of
separation between the organism and the
environment but we can also think of it
as coupling the organism to the
environment via the active states of the
organism yes when I was going in and
saying well what's the difference
between the the pebble the
the pendulums that are kind of
oscillating together and uh and an
autonomous system an agent I think a key
difference is that in the case of the
agent there is this adaptivity or what
Michael and I call adaptive active
inference uh so there's mere active
inference which is what you see in
Pebbles or in um the uh pendulums but
there's also um what we call adaptive
active inference where um that requires
that the organism is able to select
actions select policies that are going
to um minimize expected free energy or
expected prediction errors yes yes
indeed I mean again for me this this
fits very nicely into the kind of
dissection that people make of the
variational free energy equation between
the so-called K Divergence um with your
recognition density and your posterior
so what's the difference between what
you think is the posterior and what the
true posterior is that's just perceptual
inference but the the the key thing here
at least for humans is this capacity to
uh maximize model evidence so this is
the probability of why given your model
and that seems to me to be you know well
I think this is this is strongly put
within the act of inference community
that that that's reserved for animate
active beings I those animate active
beings are have what we're calling
autonomy here so right that's a a
characterization of the organization of
those systems that that goes beyond just
the mere operational closure where the
opponents are reciprocally dependent on
each other for their production that's
what operational closure means yeah and
what autonomy adds to that is is this
idea of um of self- evidencing as we
would put it in active inference terms
would probably disagree with me
describing it in that way but the
project here is to to try to bring
together active inference the free
energy principle with these ideas about
inaction from um the inactive Community
sure yeah I think a lot of these
problems come very well once we make
this distinction between systems that
minimize variational free energy and
those are abundant in the physical world
systems that do this adaptively because
that because of their autonomy because
of their
agency yes yeah yeah I see I think there
are a lot of these a lot of the
dichotomies or debates in active
inference really come down to this
fundamental issue I mean it in many ways
it depends on what your lens of analysis
is you have some people who Focus
heavily on the internal states you have
some people focus on What's called the
particle States so that includes the
blanket States and then you have some
people like a Maxwell Ram who says well
really the currency is about the mark of
across the mark of blanket the internal
and external and that you can almost
cast as you know we talk about nested
Markov blankets well that itself is a
Markov blanket which leads me to
question you know in the classical
literature about autois and operational
closure people talk about the cells
production of its cell membrane which
relies on the metabolic activity of the
cell but the metabolic activity of the
cell can only happen if there is a
coherent cell membrane that separates it
from its environment but that again
gives us this very internalist view is
it is it misspeaking to say that why
don't we just say that operational
closure can expand beyond the skin and
we could just be operationally closed in
some sense with our Eco
Niche is that reasonable or is that just
stretching the meaning of these
terms well let's back up to what you
said about perceptual inference and the
K Divergence and think about how to
understand that part of the free energy
mathematics so in the work that I did
with yala Browner we tried to to
understand the the difference between
the the actual posterior and your
inferred posterior in terms of the dis
Attunement as we describe it between the
internal Dynamics and the and the
external dynamics of the environment so
the the actual posterior there is
describing the external Dynamics and
your uh your inferred posterior
is corresponding to the internal Dynamic
so then we can unpack what K Divergence
is within this larger agent environment
system in terms of this mismatch between
the the internal and external Dynamics
so I think it's a consequence of that
and KL sometimes says this explicitly
when he's writing about Niche
construction that not only is the the
agent a model of its environment but it
applies the other way around as well
that the environment is a model of
agents that inhabit it so when we're
thinking about um uh the environment
side of things obviously we can't focus
on an individual agent because that
would then lead to some kind of
solipsism that actually you talked about
in your discussion with
Carl but uh so we shouldn't think about
the environment uh as predicting agents
just by focusing on single agents we
should instead think of group groups
communities practices and so on uh as
where the or how the niche is
constructed and then thinking about the
the niche that's constructed through our
uh through cultural evolution in part
through practices you could start to see
how there's a symmetry so that the the
environment could have a kind of
Dynamics and external Dynamics which
begins to predict what individual agents
are doing
yeah yes very nice yeah I this makes me
there number of things that come into my
head one is there's this thing called
for some reason I've been getting kind
of into the maths um to my you know I I
shouldn't be but I am but in part
because I recently spoke to Lance and
there was a lot of mass preparation that
I needed to do for that and I stumbled
across something called an Fisher
information uh metric are you familiar
what a Fisher information metric is no
cuz my m much like NE but you'll really
like this the fish information metric
basically it's very simple it
tracks how your K Divergence is doing
over time so I think this fits in very
nicely what you're talking about with
Attunement because you talk about you
and Mark and Eric talk about prediction
error uh sorry error Dynamics error
Dynamics exactly yeah but that that
implies over some o you know some dionic
over ESS and this fish information uh
metric basically tracks that in
mathematical terms which is how much you
know how great or how much bigger or how
much smaller is your KO Divergence uh
becoming over time so I thought you
would enjoy that um wonderful let's go
there eventually yes yeah we will yeah
because that's going to connect with
some other things we wanted to talk
about later on about uh about play and
intrinsic motivation
foraging quite so the other thing that
um yeah so the other thing that came
into my mind is a proposal that I made
to John vvi this this one again this is
an this is sort of Live question it was
a philosophical pondering but I quite
like it which is that our intuitions
tell us that we self-evidence given um
are the observations we make of the
environment so and that includes inter
receptive observations extra receptive
and so on my proposal is that certain
aspects of the environment also
self-evidence given the observations
that they make of us and the example
that I give of that is the rock is the
climbing wall so my idea here is that
sure the climbing wall provides the
necessary affordances for the agent of
self-evidence as a rock climber but the
rock climber provides the necessary
affordances for the climbing wall to
self-evidence as a climbing wall now
this might
be somewhat it might sound high futing
and actually be quite dull but I think
in that it it it touches upon what you
were saying about the environment in
being shaped uh through Niche
Construction as you say can begin to
manifest prediction dynamics of the
actual agents within it MH yeah I mean
the key thing about Niche construction
is that we're we're actively modifying
changing our environment in ways
contribute to to prediction era free
energy mization and we put these footh
holds in place in the climbing wall and
these finger holds and in many ways that
perit like that permits a wall that in
its own Evolution would never be a
climbing wall to become a climbing wall
um yeah yeah yeah I I really like this
notion well it is a you know it can be
seen as uh as predicting the trajectory
of the agent movements up the climbing
wall right right um yes I guess the
issue that a lot of people have here is
structured in a way that that does um
predict well that that does some of the
work that otherwise would have to be
done by the brain so this is like a
classic way of thinking about the
extended mind
you asked me about the the four e and
how to understand the four e and we
started with autonomy but we could move
to Extended mind here yeah sure and that
uh that one of the ways in which
extended mind is classically understood
is by thinking about the offloading of
computation that would otherwise need to
be done by the the brain onto structures
in the environment that then simplify
the kinds of inferences computations
that the brain has to perform so your
climbing wall example I think is an
excellent example of this kind of um
offloading of computation onto the
structure in the
environment yes I so extended I've been
thinking about the extended mind
hypothesis uh quite a bit I I plan on
doing some writing over it and I think
the big debate here is where we cast
what yakob har would call the evidential
boundary so his notion is is that in in
a very internalist way what you might
say is that the mind is doing the
prediction and everything else is being
predicted and that's why you cast your
evidential boundary because it can't be
the case that the body is both predicted
predicting and predicted and then you
have someone like Andy Clark who goes
well um you know the parity principle if
my notebook is doing as good a job as my
hippocampus and that act you know that's
part of my cognition and and in terms of
active inference we could say well that
becomes part of my predictive schema do
you take a particular do you adopt a
kind of fine line or a bright line as to
where you cast your evidential
boundary well this goes back to the the
verall quote of gr actually in an
interesting way because what what yakob
is saying is that we should put the the
Markoff blanket around the dorsal horn
and that's that's the that's the
candidate that he gives for where the
the Markoff blanket might be relative to
which self- evidencing then takes place
uh so that would then imply that that
anything that I'm describing as
offloading is um an example of uh self-
evidencing where the structure of the
environment is causally very important
but it isn't actually part of what's
doing the self-
evidencing so the the way to think about
that is in terms of this notion of
embedding rather than uh extending the
mind or extending cognition nice uh so
so yakob could well agree that um that
the environment here is causally very
important and the way that the
environment is structured but all of the
inference is now going to be done uh uh
through processes that that are mediated
by exchanges between the brain and the
body at the dorsal
horn and you know well there's many
things to say about that uh so um what
one thing I want to point to is a paper
in Synthesia and also the the book that
I wrote with Michael kof where we argue
um
that uh there there's reasons to think
that the um self- evidencing system is
an agent again and that that agent can
incorporate into its body uh resources
that are external to the body so that
they become part of uh what's doing the
the self- evidencing or what's doing the
inference and
so um if you think going back to where
we started that the the free energy
minimizing system is a an agent an agent
that has this property of biological
autonomy rather than heteronomy and I
didn't answer your question of what
heteronomy is so come back to that in a
minute um but if you think that the free
energy minimizing system is
biologically
autonomous then that system can begin to
have uh an
organization that
incorporates uh resources that are
external to the organism in the
environment and those resources can
include things like the structure of the
climbing wall or the white lines that
are painted onto the road that you use
to simplify your your um your driving
behavior you just follow the white lines
and that gives you a very simple
heuristic that you can use for for
minimizing free
energy
yes one paper that's really informed my
thoughts on this is Andy Clark's how to
knit your own marov blanket it's just
like a wonderful uh it's a wonderful
kind of deflation of all the tensions in
this area because you can just say well
the markco blanket is is an abstraction
in the sense that it's always embedded
within another Mark of blanket which is
always embedded within another Mark of
blanket and where you choose to cast
that Mark of blanket as we've discussed
many times on this podcast can be often
just an instrumental tool and and but
more importantly than that is if we do
take it seriously that there is a mark
of blanket it doesn't need to be fixed
so we can have a process ontology rather
than a substance ontology whereby when
I'm in my car for me to self-evidence
it's I incorporate the car's Dynamic so
that me and the car it's it's sort of
recursive my sort of A and B becomes a
new a and we can scale this way you know
all the way up to social or Global
Dynamics but I think the important let's
not get but I think the important point
is no one's no one's asking anyone to
find the one markof
blanket no so there's going to be a
nesting of markof blankets that's
absolutely right yeah yeah always and
and once you start to to see how Markoff
blankets are nested then uh you can
start to think about well what's the
relationship between the Markoff
blankets and that's where we've argued
you can get the an account of how to
formalize autonomy using the Markoff
blanket concept because you can start to
think about how the the sensory and
active states that are forming the
markof blanket enter into these kind of
reciprocal relations of dependence that
the organization of the system then
depends on so you can start to get a
formalization of operational closure out
of the relationship between the the
different Markoff blankets in a system
that has a a nested markof blanket
organization so that's one thing you can
do also do what we've been talking about
here of thinking about how some of the
Markoff blankets in this complex system
are going to be located outside of the
boundaries of the of the
organism so the sensory and active
states that that are forming the markof
blanket could start to uh be outside of
the uh the
sensorium they could so think about a
spider in its web that's the example
that Michael and I use as a very
intuitive example of this that the the
spider can start to use the movements in
the web as its sensory and active states
to catch prey for
instance right so then the web and the
spider are uh forming a single system
there's a kind of extended phenotype we
could talk about that forms between the
The Spider and the
web and also his notebook can also be
described in this way so the sensory and
active states that form uh the boundary
of the extended cognitive system can
could now be uh could now involve the
notebook and the writing down of things
in the notebook the looking up of
information in The Notebook B and so
on yes yeah see the thing is I like that
my my only sort of naive
reticence is because we're
conscious and this is such a sticking
point but I think where some of the
cortico centrism comes from is the kind
of presumption say this before but you
know that Michael and I argue for
extended Consciousness so we maybe we
get there a bit later on there's one
more thing I want to say about the the
extended mind and how um active
inference is relevant to the extended
mind
discussions um and this relates to the
idea of recruitment of external
resources and how recruitment works so
for a long time Andy Clark's argued that
the the brain is is a kind of um lazy
brain that tries to simplify its
computations as much as possible for
evolutionary reasons so you could relate
it to the principle of least action
probably this idea of efficient
computation um
and sometimes to efficiently compute it
makes sense to offload that computation
onto the environment so this is classic
kind of situated cognition idea that
goes back to the
1990s um maybe even further back than
that um so how does that uh how do you
then weigh up what's going to be the
most efficient way to Sol a
problem do you solve the problem just by
relying on your onboard biological
Hardware or do you offload the problem
solving onto the world and recruit
external resources so this is called the
recruitment problem because it's a
problem about how you soft assemble a
cognitive system on the fly in such a
way as to uh as efficiently as possible
Compu a solution to a
problem and uh what Andy Clark's been
arguing in recent work is that the the
recruitment problem is
solved by uh your uh
your um imperative to minimize
prediction error over time to minimize
expected prediction error or expected
free energy so we can give a kind of
account of how it is that cognitive
systems whose boundaries extend beyond
the
organism and come to recruit certain
external resources to solve problems in
terms of uh free energy minimization or
in terms of expected free energy
minimization that can become a policy
that's infered that the most efficient
way to solve a problem is by recruiting
external resources that simplify the
computations that would otherwise have
to be done inside of the hge that's
really really nice I'm writing that down
because I really like that
uh cool that's that's awesome okay yeah
there's a paper that we can link you to
in the australasian Journal of
philosophy that Andy published um I
think last year um there's a there's a
reply to yakob Hoy as well called
busting out yes yeah yeah yeah that also
makes these these same sorts of
arguments that and in that paper Andy
ties it to uh precision and to precision
as kind of sculpting the effective
connectivity of the brain in a context
sensitive way yeah so he has the idea
that when you're Computing Precision
sometimes those computations will lead
you to to increase the gain on um
on well I'm going to put it in terms of
the the sensory and active states that
are external to the body uh that relate
to the structures in the environment so
then the as you put it before the
Markoff blanket is not fixed it it kind
of extends to include those resources in
the external
environment although that said there's a
there's a way of modeling sort of um a
basian graph for example or a pom DP
scheme whereby that which you deploy
Precision waiting over is not
necessarily incorporated into your own
markof blanket so there's a really nice
paper by mitz and colleagues 2019 where
they talk about selective attention and
how selective attention needs to be
governed by the capacity for cognizers
to to pay or or to downregulate task
irrelevant objects let's
say but that doesn't mean that the task
irrelevant objects are automatically
Incorporated within the self markof
blanket it's just that they have gain
control or there's gain control over
them um no but I was thinking a
different case where it's not so much
the task irrelevant objects that you're
now dis attending to but the task
relevant objects that you're attending
to and how the Precision mechanism can
be what explains how those task relevant
objects get to
become uh a part of an extended
cognitive system uh so it's the opposite
of the case that you were describing
where they were describing how task
relevant objects are not selected yeah
I'm thinking about the case where a task
relevant object that is external to the
body like the book or the spiders web
are uh now attended to because they are
uh precisely because they're task
relevant they allow you to to solve a
problem in a much more efficient way
than you would if you just relied on
your brain to clarify um I I I was s of
introducing it as the kind of downrating
of task irrelevant um objects but it's
it precisions are zero some game so up
of the gain so oh I see okay I guess
it's all
relative on the task relevant stuff sure
sure I think I won't misspeak people can
see it themselves but the outcome is the
same um in the sense that it's all
relative so precisions are zero some
game so if it goes down here it's going
to go up
here saying is you don't want to include
the task stuff yeah yeah yeah yeah so
that's exactly their point yeah yeah you
do want to include the task relevant
stuff that's what the soft assembly of
the cognitive system is it's the it's
the selecting what's relevant to your
problem solving in this context I guess
my question here is does it make a
difference whether we downregulate task
irrelevant objects because in doing so
right if we just think of a landscape
where everything is equal in pressing
these down you get relative gain on
those which have not been suppressed
versus actively inflating the Precision
of task relevant objects do we not get
the same outcome just in relev uh
relative terms so I think what's super
interesting here is that Precision turns
out to be doing what John VY cause
relevance realization yeah so uh the
model that you've just been talking
about is so which prediction errors
should be treated as Salient or uh
reliable for so that they get to
influence future
processing um and so you you are
focusing on the the error signals which
are downway so not treated as Salient
because their task
irrelevant I've been talking about the
error signals which where you turn up
the gain because they are Salient sure
they are relevant so this is part of the
the problem of how uh as VY calls it how
do we solve the in a particular context
the problem of what's relevant and
what's irrelevant
yeah the frame problem yeah yeah yeah
yes no you you might indeed you might
well be right the mid
tole 2019 with Frist and frame it that
way again it's been a while since I read
it but it it converges on the same point
which is that the human organism the the
cognizer has the capacity even before it
even glances over even before it does
the iser card to have this
disambiguation which I just think is
stunning and I think you can scale that
up towards the fact that we you know in
in the classical um bias competition
Theory they just desimo and Duncan
basically just postulate that go being
uh go representations inflate that which
uh you know inflate the stimuli that
correlate with the goal so if I'm
looking for my Ginger friend you know I
have this template of Ginger and
everything Ginger start everything orang
or Ginger starts in increasing in game
control what inference gives you is a
really really nice I think it gives you
a really nice way of modeling that
although I don't think it's been done
yet which relies on sort of deep
parametric modeling and about um mental
action yielding Precision waiting over
sensory expectations I might have a
mental action okay I want to uh have
high Precision over anything that's
Ginger and then in turn I'm gonna act so
as to confirm that I think the other
thing just for the audiences and
something that has really become quite
clear to me is there's difference
between precision and precision waiting
and this is something that I think needs
to be articulated a little bit more in
the active inference literature in so
far as Precision is just the inverse
entropy of a probab probability
distribution or you can just say it's
standard deviation but Precision waiting
is actually the deployment of uh well it
could be considered gain control but
gain control is not just based on the
Precision of a signal because when I'm
so if the Precision of the so they
people talk about attention being the
optim ization of What's called the a
matrix which is the likelihood
distribution so what are the CH given uh
given a state what's the likelihood of
this observation but just having a
really strong onetoone mapping between
those two doesn't mean you're going to
pay attention just to that because if
I'm looking for my Ginger friend there
might be loads of things out there which
have very precise mappings to their
causes but I'm ignoring them so they
might be very precise observations but
they don't matter um so that's just to
say that I think people I think at least
it needs to become more articulated
within the literature exactly what this
difference is although the as I said the
Deep parametric modeling of it hasn't
been done yet as far as I'm aware so
there's plenty of work to be done there
but yeah John this is right up John
Street okay what you said there about it
if you're interested in finding your
friend with ginger hair that's the thing
that matters to you so that's Vision I
think that's really in in an important
point because it it makes the connection
between attention and uh and your goals
y yeah and it also makes the link
between attention and what you care
about so what matters to you and yeah as
an agent so finding your friend matters
to you that's something that you care
about yeah yeah yeah friend so there's a
link here between precision and and
emotion which I think um in the work
I've been doing with Mark Miller we
would argue leads to an embodied view so
going back to the ease now we could
think about the E of embodiment um we
can also think about the E of
extendedness some more here but thinking
about the E of embodiment the reason
that we should think of precision as
embodied is because what you care about
is sculpting uh modulating what is given
Precision in a particular context so in
your example what's given Precision is
is finding your
friend that's uh and and that's given
Precision because that matters to you
because that's important to you because
right you care about your friend because
we're because we're autonomous because
we act according to our own norms and
values of which which we've made that's
right that's part of it h so um people
talk about autonomy as then
entailing uh making or meaning making
because uh based on your
autonomy uh there are then Norms
meanings uh values that become intrinsic
to your biological
organization uh so in this case the
value of your friend you're caring about
your friend can be thought of as
something that falls out of the uh free
energy minimizing
Machinery um because that Machinery is
the Machinery of
uh an autonomous being so values meaning
and so on become intrinsic to uh the
sustaining the maintaining of the
organization of that being sure I'm GNA
I'm going to spit more on idea and I'm
curious about what you think about it so
people take this idea of the
relationship between attention and
values and inflate it quite strongly and
I don't mean that in a disparaging way
because I think some of the work is very
powerful but for example Le someone like
a Jordan Peterson or Jonathan Pou or
even John vvi might say well what is
sacred the term sacred is that which you
pay most attention to or that which cap
or that which governs your attentional
schema so for example you could see we
have a hierarchy of values so why do I
want to earn money because I want to go
on holiday why do I want to go on
holiday because I want to be happy why
do I want to be happy and then Aristotle
would say well that's just that's it you
got it do you think that we can do you
think that's a viable way of recapturing
the idea of the Sacred if that means
anything to you in terms of
computational attentional
mechanisms wow that's a big question I
know so uh how do we get to to wisdom
and the sacred and so on from uh from
this kind of computational Machinery uh
I think there there's an interesting
story to be told about that um and I
think we can get there uh but it
requires a number of different steps
sure along the way to connect attention
as it's uh modeled using Precision to uh
attentional schemes as you just
described them that could be shaped by
uh religious beliefs for instance in the
beliefs in sacred and so on
um and no I think we can go there
because um this free energy principle
once you think of Markoff blankets as
nested yeah can be applied to very
complex um groups
communities by thinking about how um the
agents that make up that group are now
part of collective
systems uh where it makes sense to think
of those Collective systems as also
minimizing expected free energy so one
of the routes I would go here would be
to to think about cultural
ecosystems and think about what you just
called the the
sacred uh and the the sorts of
attentional schemas that are involved
there in terms of these these larger
Collective um free energy minimizing
systems yes yeah exactly move I would
make here and going back to the
individual MH um and how an an
individual may may have an experience of
the Sacred how to make sense of that
well uh you're getting into very deep uh
aspects of Consciousness when you think
about uh subjective experiences of the
Sacred and and very deep Notions of
meaning making um and your friend
example that that got us into this was
was an example of a meaningful well a
source of meaning in people's lives
which is comes from the
the con the social connectedness between
people um that that's a source of
meaning U but obviously the sacred is
also a profound source of meaning for
people and but it's a very thick concept
so how to make sense of the kind of
meaning that people get from the sacred
uh the meaning in life that that gives
people uh using these these ideas of
predictive processing would require a
much more complex story than how the
value that we place in our uh our
connectedness to one another um that
could be traced back to something that's
more I think to do with primary
emotions the or basic emotions to go to
the the emotion literature something
that we see in animals as well and that
probably is tied to
neurotransmitters but the
sacred um the kind of meaning that
people find in the
sacred to account for the way that that
gives meaning to people's lives in terms
of predictive processing I think can be
done but it requires a much uh more
complex
story yes I think I think some of that
story will come one from your notion of
nested
affordances but not that these nested
affordances are separate from one
another there's a very important idea in
predictive coding uh literature that the
higher levels of the predictive coding
hierarchy contextualized and constrain
the activity at the lower levels so for
example I have a and the higher levels
track longer term
regularities so they're slower they're
more
entrenched and they constrain and
contextualize what happens uh with the
tracking of slower faster fluctuations
to give an
example uh I might I I've written this
actually in this new paper that I've
written so my beliefs that I want to go
to France in June is based off a higher
order the belief that summer in France
is quite a nice
experience and that is going to
constrain every action that I do so it's
going to constrain the way that I go on
Skyscanner and B my flight but then the
other important thing is that those
lower levels also interact with the
higher levels so again I give this
example if it rains every day in June in
nce I'm probably GNA take out an
umbrella on July first despite the fact
that I had this high order belief that
it's always sunny in France in the
summer so I think this this um
prediction this trickling prediction
down and the cascading or the uh the
movement up of prediction error is maybe
where this answer is going to
lie why as you say why we get this
notion of meaning in Life or the sacred
or this particular phenomenological
Essence I think is up for grabs I don't
think anyone knows as of yet but I think
it is going to be done in this kind of
deep in the modeling sense this deep
ometric modeling so something
AK I think what I like about what you
just said was that um when you think
about the experience of the Sacred it
seems that there's a whole Rich story to
be told there about what the sacred is
exactly so you're looking at a narrative
of some sort and there's a good argument
for thinking at least in terms of the
self model yeah what you find at the the
higher layers of the self model are
going to be narrative type structures
that connect your self in the past to
who you are in the present where you're
going in the future so where are you
going on holiday in your example but uh
so it's the there's a narrative
structure to uh both to the experiences
of the Sacred I would argue and and to
uh what you're uh doing when you're
planning your summer holiday right and
so how would do we think about a
narrative well you could think about
that just within the individual in terms
of for instance the the mental time
travel idea the mode Network that is
involved both in Imagining the future
and in remembering the past so you could
think of the process of constructing a
narrative as just something that happens
within the
individual or you can think no when it
comes to very complex experiences like
the experience of the Sacred the
construction of the narrative there is
something that involves a much larger
system uh a collect Ive system where the
uh beliefs about the sacred that are
used to make inferences for instance are
ones that uh we need to uh explain in
terms of some dynamics of a larger
Collective
system uh so what's at the top I think
is what I'm asking you here you have the
idea that that the top layers of the
generative model are
constraining um the
decision making the SEL inference of of
policies at the lower levels and that's
that's absolutely right but what's at
the top can be thought of using the idea
of Andreas rupor and uh and Chris FR in
terms of what they call uh top top
interactions so they can be thought of
in terms of interactions that take place
within cultural systems or within a
cultural
ecosystem uh so to make sense of this
kind of um uh experience in terms of uh
the inferential processes that minimize
free energy we need to look at a a much
larger Collective system here not just a
a system inside of the individual and
that's another way of thinking about
extended mind where we're thinking of
Mind here as distributed over uh a
cultural ecosystem not as something
that's in side of
individuals yes that's wonderful that's
wonderful yeah so I've been thinking a
lot about these self models but I think
you're absolutely right the sacred Taps
into self- evidencing of almost a world
model um a a world model that is not not
for one but for what you call what
vicenin and you go and and you call a
way of life form of EX form of life form
of life way of life I love as well a
form of life form of life I I was
literally thinking I'm not going to mess
that one up okay a form of life in the
sense that a form of life is it's
connected with a way of life and
certainly the sacred is connected with
the way of life sure
but yeah go IDE form of life where we
Define that as um as a a regular pattern
of activity that can be found within a a
group or a community right so perhaps
it's a notion that scales but you can
apply it at a collective that's the the
key idea that's relevant
here a species as a form of life or as
members of that form of life so
individuals as forms of life and when we
think about autonomy again biological
autonomy that's that's a way of thinking
about what form of a form of life is at
the scale of an individual
organism so it's a scaling notion yeah
yeah yeah like the Markoff blanket is a
scaling notion because that it can be
applied to very big things like
economies and cultural ecosystems and it
can be applied to very small things like
cells or um or molecules
particles yeah this is this is super
interesting again yeah exactly scale is
really the relevant thing here the
question is what what what is at the
highest level of of the form of life's
generative
model and there are answers that some
people are posited I mean
Consciousness um there's there's this
idea at least um I don't think they
would have expanded this to like a panus
view but it certainly lends I would say
some it leans quite heavily on pan
psychism you know Maxwell RAM and Ma
alaras in this notion that Consciousness
is this the uppermost Mark of blanket in
the
brain well this is not too dissimilar to
Someone Like Jordan Peterson who says
that you know the voice of God is
actually the voice of Consciousness and
and and that's the guiding spirit so
again we're postulating but I think
there's a really
interesting framework set up there for
anyone who wants to get into that which
is what is the fundamental thing that's
constraining us and contextualizing us
and I don't I just don't think it's
survival I don't think it can just be
biological imperatives I think maybe
it's just me being romantic but I I
sense that it transcends that
um yeah so there are two things I want
to say on that before you move on so
sure sure please the first is that going
back to the ROP sto and fith paper about
the top top interactions what they were
interested in that paper is that the
idea that what you have at the top in
top down control they were thinking
about executive functions for instance
is um something that in the prefrontal
cortex for instance that might be the
source of will or willpower or
agency and they were arguing that
actually it makes sense to think that um
that the executive functions could be uh
unfolding not within individuals but
within larger groups or within diads or
within social systems so so the the role
of uh executive functioning or top- down
control would then be done in
interaction with other people rather
than something that unfolds within
individuals uh so that that's a way of
thinking about what's at the top in
terms of topown control or executive
functioning where we think think that
the executive functioning is now the
control processes are uh in the sense of
the thing that might be doing
willpower is something that is social
and in involves social interactions
rather than something that happens
inside of the head oh that so nice oh
that's yeah I like that okay that's y
that's really good that's one thing I
want to say about that and then the
Consciousness being at the top in top
down control well again we have this
idea of willpower as involing conscious
intention making or something like that
and and then there's all of the
arguments about whether the the wheel is
epip phenomenal or is it just an
illusion like Daniel Wagner's work and
um and and then people that want to say
no it will the will is tied to
Consciousness and or people who want to
say no all intentional action is just
generated unconsciously and there isn't
really any work for the will to do
anymore based on like liit type
arguments and so yeah there is a
connection between Consciousness and and
this idea of executive
functioning uh not it's a bit different
from what Maxwell and Ma are doing I
think that there is a connection there
maybe it ties more closely with what
Adam saffron tries to do where he tries
to bring this like herous idea together
with Free Will and that's part of his
work yes I mean I mean verel said what
that we're composed of micro
identities um I think there's always an
open question about how seriously you
take this notion of uh
self-construction once you start getting
to the very the very top or the very
bottom level of the generative hierarchy
so what a minimal self model might look
like um but that's that's that's a
different question maybe we'll come to
self modeling so we I wanted to finish
the thought on the will on Consciousness
sorry because I didn't quite get to the
end of it but yeah the thought that the
the path I was on was that um was going
to take us back to narrative again
actually so um so if we think about the
narrative layers of the self model I
think there's there's a good good reason
to think that they they might be where
you need to look to understand uh will
for instance will power yeah in that um
so Elizabeth paser in her work on um on
intention makes this distinction between
present directed and future directed
intentions which are like what we call
plans in in active inference the future
directed
intentions and those know you can think
of as coming from your narrative about
who you are those future directed
intentions like your example of going on
holiday to France that's a a future
directed intention that then sculpts the
decisions that you make when you go onto
your uh your flight
booking oh sorry can we just pause a
minute sorry about that no not
all uh so we're talking about present
directness and future dirting this
exactly um and how the narrative might
be what uh connects together
your present intentions with your future
intentions and your your past
experiences I think your example of
holidaying in France Illustrated that
very well so you have the past
experiences of France being beautiful in
the summer and that then feeds into your
uh your plans for the future leading you
to form particular intentions in the
present absolutely so so the narrative
we can think of as uh as at the higher
level doing the work of controlling
planning in a way that you might think
of gets you intentional action so
actions which where you could uh think
that the intention is the cause of your
actions which is what we're looking for
when we think about Free
Will that's that's excellent yeah yeah
yeah absolutely I completely agree um
yeah there be some wonderful ideas here
um so just want to point people in
direction of uh yakob lonowski work with
Carl
they sort of point to uh the depth of
temporal modeling Carl has done this in
his solo work as well to be really what
underlies the construction or the
generation of what they call an
epistemic agent model and this is
something that I spoke about in in the
paper which is that an epistemic agent
model can use uh past experience past
knowledge to inform allostasis
counterfactual reasoning and all these
things we associate with
planning so that's but that all comes
from this really wonderful work that car
done with with people like um Jakob
lowski okay that's yeah that's that's
excellent wonderful okay we we we're
talking exactly the same language which
is which is awesome now I want to go on
to something maybe a little different
and uh I'm gonna make a I'm gonna say a
quote firsty uh just to frame the
conversation so Lawrence Shapiro who
you'll be very you know you'll be very
aware of his work he says I challenge
anyone to explain how I managed recently
to travel from Madison to Cologne purely
in terms of my sensitive responding to
Natural signs now he says this in
response in a review of hotto and
Mayan's books so uh the 2013 and the
2017 book now I just finished the 2013
book uh and I I and I've been delving a
little bit into the sorts of critiques
so evans's critiques uh Lawrence's
critiques but again I'm not an expert um
in my conversation with Chris I actually
had to go back and sort of clarify but
Harter and may make this basic point
that basil or basic cognition is
contentless representation free um but
you do have these higher order forms of
cognition which are scaffolded of social
interactions symbolic systems
developmental schema uh which are
basically about public language
use now you if I'm speak correctly have
a skepticism of this distinction between
higher and lower forms of
cognition and you in your paper on
affordances
2014 say we suggest in says you say we
find this commonly made distinction
between lower and higher forms of
cognition unhelpful we suggest instead
that the relevant distinction is better
marked by differences in level of
ability or expertise in doing things
with the affordances of the environment
so my first question
is do you think that cognition is
representation
free uh and if so to what degree is it
all of it is it just the lower order the
basic cognition what what were your
thoughts in that
domain
yeah so representations we're going to
go into representations so I've been
getting really into it and I know it's a
very hot area and people get angry at
each other so we're not no one's going
to get angry um and feel we don't have
to go into it no I'm not going to get
angry certainly not uh it doesn't make
me
angry but the the issue comes up when we
think about the generative model and and
and what exactly uh BAS and priors are
so there's this purely statistical
understanding of what basy and priors
are and and what they turn out to be in
the generative model and that I think we
can unpack without bringing in anything
like representations or content um this
is a controversial position so most
people would think as soon as you've got
a internal model of the world then that
internal model has to be a a
representation uh because they think
well it meets all of the conditions for
represent ation like for instance
there's a structural isomorphism between
the model and the environment where that
isomorphism can be
exploited uh so made use of by
Downstream processes to infer to make
decisions and so on uh so it looks like
the internal model the generative model
meets all of the conditions for being a
a representation a full-fledged
representation and I think it does
doesn't I think it's just a mathematical
construct the generative model uh that
uh can be used to model
autonomy um and um we can think of the
the agent not as having a model yeah so
as um instantiating and a model of the
internal uh sorry a model of the
external Dynamics in its internal
Dynamics yeah that's what I've been
saying yeah but um rather as um just a
mathematical construct that describes
the Dynamics the self-organizing
Dynamics of the agent in its coupling
with the environment so we can give a
contentless uh content free
representation free account of what the
generative model is that's part of what
I want to say here MH now you ask me uh
does that then commit me to
something like hat and Mayan's
distinction between basic and uh
cognition which is
non-representational doesn't involve
representations and uh and non-basic
cognition which is where which is
content involving or representation
involving yeah and to answer that
question we need to know what
representations are because they clearly
exist um so it's just the issue is
whether it makes sense to think of the
brain as having content bearing states
are so where exactly do representations
come in and there I think we need to
look at Classic kinds of examples of
what representations are in human life
so we find representations when we uh
use pictures and images and
diagrams and those are uh are coming
from cultural practices like uh the use
of diagrams to do science or the use of
figures in right writing articles or uh
the use of um uh pictures when we're
doing art uh that can be traced back to
making paintings on Cave
walls um so these are um representation
based practices um but they come from
culture they don't come from uh what the
brain is doing uh so that's one example
of what a representation is that it's an
image or a
picture a second example of what a
representation might be is a a a state
that carries semantic
content so what is semantic content well
it's um
a type of meaning where uh there's a
determinacy to that meaning such that
you can
specify truth conditions conditions of
satisfaction that the state that's
carrying that uh Mantic content can be
evaluated for so the state can be
correct or incorrect it can be evaluated
as correct or incorrect true or false
and so on and the problem with the the
kinds of states that we find within a
generative model is that they don't have
the kind of determinant contents that
map
onto uh semantic
meanings so when it comes to um making
the translation from Shannon information
mhm to semantic information where
semantic information has this
determinacy um this specificity to it
there's a there's a
mismatch uh we have to explain how to
get from what is mere co-variation or
correlation which is what you're dealing
with when you're thinking about Shannon
information yeah information that's
specific enough that you can start to
say that the the organism could be wrong
in how it's taking the world to be or
wrong in uh the the way that it states
are states that are have meaning for the
organism so that it's that mismatch that
makes me think no it's just not right to
to think of the generative model as uh
in terms of representation we can just
make sense of it as a mathematical
object that is tracking statistical
patterns captured by the sorts of
variables parameters that we um that we
use to write down the the generative
model long answer but hopefully it gets
some of the issues on the table for us
no it's wonderful it frames it frames it
very nicely and and that is precisely
actually in that 2013 book at least what
harto and Mayan say that just to repeat
what you said that you there it's It
seems impossible to go from co-variance
to content uh and I think they actually
have a principle for it because why not
um yeah yeah of course lots of
philosophers don't agree with them about
that so Nick Shay who's who's a good
colleague of of Chris fris and they've
worked together he has a whole book
where he lays out how you can get uh
semantic meaning from uh adding some
extra conditions to co-variation and
right he thinks you need both indicators
so that's what Shannon information gets
you and also consumers of those states
that indicate something very roughly and
so once you have like a richer account
he thinks that you can give an argument
for thinking well no there there is real
semantic meaning here not just um but
that's one thing he wants to say yeah sh
also has this like more nuanced picture
where there's just different kinds of
content that we need to bring in and uh
hat and may really focus on a very rich
demanding sort of content find in
language that a paradigm example of
representation and what what Shay tries
to do is show well there's more U
there's less demanding Notions weaker
Notions which still qualify as
content yes okay well yes so and Chris
didn't have too much time for the
radical in activists
um most most uh cognitive
neuroscientists have no time for radical
in activists and and it's their own
fault because the radical in activists
are so kind of polarizing in how they uh
engage in this discussion right so kind
of yeah exactly so I have no skill in
the game so I'm not gonna get no I have
no passion here but I think I think so I
think Harter and Mayan obviously spend a
lot of time criticizing um this notion
of cognition as content or the mark of
the cognitive being
representation where I think there are
viable critiques of their book and their
work is the alter alternative is
somewhat not particularly at least
explicated in any great depth um they
say for example the idea that organisms
are so they they want to endorse the
idea that organisms are informationally
sensitive are ye that they exploit
correspondences in their environments to
adaptively guide their actions while
denying that it follows that they take
in store or process informational
content now this notion of exploiting
correspondences sounds very much like
there's some there's a function there
which indicates something else now that
is representation right under a dreian
account of what representation is now on
the other hand if they say well no all
we're talking about here is just the
responsivity of the organism the the
adaptivity the good jobs that they do by
responding to
stimuli well then I think this is the
point that Shapiro makes or maybe it's
Heaven this is this could just their
teio semiotics what they call their teos
semiotics is no different from
behaviorism
and actually it's even more radical than
the behaviorist because the behaviorist
all the behaviorist said was well it's
just not really part of the scientific
purview to talk about internal States uh
because all we can observe a behavioral
um you know behavioral action they
didn't even they didn't necessarily deny
um content bearing States they just
thought it wasn't worth the examination
until Mr Chomsky and so do you like is
there a way out of this um conundrum
that one it's we find it very difficult
to get content out of covariance and
there is coari but then the other hand
it's very difficult to account for
adaptive Behavior solely in terms of
covariant so uh on the behaviorist thing
and I think H and may well certainly
Mayan is willing to just bite the bullet
on Behavior oh really fantastic so
behaviorism is often depicted as this
like devilish position that nobody
should hold anymore since the cognitive
Revolution but sure some caricatures and
Straw Men about what behaviorism is
exactly that uh I think May in at least
is in in the business of and also Louise
Barrett and uh some of the work that
she's done they're trying to uh correct
for mistaken interpretations of what
behaviorism actually means so that is
part of the U the radical inactive
project at least some people have
pursuing that within radical in
activism um so how to go well why is
indication that serves a particular
function not sufficient for uh for
Content according to hat and M U um why
couldn't we use that model and just have
a completely
contentless uh explanation of behavior
well they think it's not sufficient
because it doesn't get us the spe
specific Take On The World world that's
required to say that an organism could
be
mistaken and any any definition of uh
content or meaning uh requires that that
that the state that's the carrying the
content could
be mistaken it could be
misrepresenting how things are in terms
of its uh that State's particular Take
On The World and so when we try to build
in specificity and get that out of
function
yes that there's uh there's
long-standing problems that that project
has run
into again it fails to get us the
specificity that we
require so where the debate's kind of
got to and this is Nick Shay's position
is that you just need to to have a more
relaxed view of what specificity is and
such that it depends on your your
question that you're asking what kinds
of questions you have in doing
psychology or cognitive Neuroscience
well dictate uh whether you need more or
less
specificity uh so you relative to your
questions you can get the kind of
specificity you need to talk about
content we shouldn't think that there's
one size fits all picture that's going
to answer all of all of the uh the
different questions that we might have
because each question might require a
different level of gr granularity or
specificity sure well not to try and
offer a one-sized fit all but I'm
curious about uh
your position so moving sorry I've been
saying what's been going on elsewhere
and the discussions not no no no no not
at all that's my fault as well I it's
all the framing which is excellent and I
also wanted to backtrack on the hard
turn myio thing because uh it was it was
dealt with quite briefly in my
conversation with Chris and there were
certain things I had to go in and
clarify post Haw so it's useful so
people you know are aware of these
clarifications um so what what what do I
think about all of this well I'm
sympathetic to the idea that that we
when we think about what representations
and content is then we should this is
where my phenomenological background
comes in yes we need to go back to lived
experience which is where the notion of
intentionality was first introduced by
brentano and H other phenomenologists um
so intentionality has its origins in
lived
experience um
and then when when we try to deploy this
notion in doing
science um then we've taken up a
particular attitude towards the world
the scientific
attitude um but the notion of content
and meaning itself derives from uh from
uh our perception and thought as
conscious beings uh so there's a a
bigger question here about how to uh
make phenomenology fit together with the
uh the naturalistic world viiew that we
get when we start to do cognitive
neuroscience and um yeah this goes back
to another one of the ease the ease of
the inactive uh Camp uh where going back
to the embodied mind of verella Thompson
and rash from 1991
MH the critique that made of cognitivist
cognitive science a cognitive science
that thinks just cognition is
information processing of some kind yeah
was that it doesn't have room for Human
Experience if you think of uh of
cognition as information processing how
do we then account for uh the what's
described phenomenologically when we
think of
intentionality as a structure of Human
Experience expence so intentionality
here means the directedness of the Mind
upon
objects and the idea of intentionality
is that you you're always working with a
a kind of relation between subject and
object so intentionality is supposed to
be
describing a a mode of experience that
involves a essential relationality
between subjects and their world heigo
went on to talk about this in terms of
being in the world talk
with in a beautiful episode thank you
that was wonderful yeah there's loads of
things that come up here I mean so first
you're not going to find an enemy of yes
please go ahead if you got yeah just uh
know where I look for intentionality and
meaning is in lived experience and then
that raises the question of how to bring
together how to make room for what was
described in phenomenology ology when
they were describing the human mind in
cognitive science in cognitive
Neuroscience um and verella Thompson and
Ros put to put forward this idea of
mutual
constraints that what is described
phenomenal
logically uh is a constraint on the
kinds of explanations that we give in
cognitive science and what's described
in cognitive science likewise
constraints that's why this is a mutual
constraint
what we can make sense of
phenomenologically so there's a kind of
um what's described by uh verella in
terms of
um a what's the term he uses now Maxwell
also uses this in one of his papers on
computational neurop phenomenal oh yeah
it's um there's a kind of generative um
passage between
phenomenology and cognitive science that
that you get from this Mutual constraint
yes yeah yeah yeah uh yes I was saying
yes he says from generative models to
generative
passages exactly yeah so you're not
gonna find generative but but the idea
is that we ought to be able to have this
kind of um passage so bridge that goes
between phenomenology which was not
describing anything in a scientific way
but trying to go back to lived
experience there ought to be like a a
bridge that takes us from phenomenology
to what we can now model computationally
using the free energy principle that's
the idea of generative passage well
that's the game that I'm in um and
enjoying that's the game I'm in as well
and it's fun yeah I'm
enjoy involved in this within the active
inference
Community yes it g no it gives a
wonderful way of doing it back to um
know to to the original embodied mind
idea it that book The embodied mind was
what I found as an undergraduate that
that brought me into this field um and
it's very inspiring it tries to bring
together phenomenology Buddhism and
cognitive science uh through this idea
of
inaction um I still think it's a
brilliant book I would recommend it to
everybody Evan wrote it when he was
young and verella was U later stage in
his career so some of the ideas I think
are developed much better in in mind and
life which you also mentioned
earlier um but but just because of its
kind of broad brush Strokes it makes it
very readable and and so everybody can
kind of get on board with the project at
least sure yeah I'm very much enjoying
mind and life um yeah so as you know
you're not going to find an enemy of
phenomenology here um I like my haiger
and hle and Merlo Ponte I particularly
like like
draus um and draus has a draus I think
is an important addition to this
conversation because I hate to go back
to them but well I don't hate to go back
to them but Hatter and may actually
mentioned draus dra's notion of skillful
coping skillful action as exhibiting
intentionality and bear in mind yes it's
not basic cognition according to them is
not contentful but it is still
intentional in some sense it's
targeting um but they use d to say well
he doesn't there are no mental
representations or um content and I
build off some of this in this notion of
flow states which I think are a really
example uh interesting example of which
which Taps into some of these ideas but
the problem with this is that
draf I don't think and I think this is
the point that actually Evan Thompson
made that draf wouldn't say that those
states are contentless and I wouldn't
say those states are
contentless rather they're intentionally
contentful but in a way that's not
representational in a way that it's not
like there's a representation which
stands for something precise in the
world to which you can attribute uh well
that function you could attribute a a a
truth
claim rather there are these Norms that
are governed by perceptual perception
and action
Loops um and this biological autonomy
that we've been
discussing and but ra but there's still
this intentional content which he would
call skillful coping um and I think you
could consider to be this kind of Auto
tocity that comes out of
flow so what does what what what does
the what do the phenomenologist
contribute more broadly Beyond draus
although he does rest his arguments a
lot on Merlo Ponte um about the role of
content yeah so um let's first of all go
back to the the categories of the ready
to hand and the present at hand that
yeah
that dfus really focuses on in his uh in
his work uh interpreting division one of
hiiga Being and Time um
so when we're dealing with the the ready
to hand uh um we're behaving in a way
that our our actions are are drawn from
us by the solicitations of the world
that's the kind of phrasing that he
often and gibs and that we Eric and Eric
geld and I and Y
Browner uh the three of us have been
very much inspired by Gus's reading of
the ready to hand um so it's this
responsiveness to the solicitations so
solicitations are for us uh affordances
which stand out from uh the
surroundings as relevance or meaningful
salience to what the agent is doing so
the classic example that haiger uses
which you know from the conversation
Marlin is the the hammer and the nail I
think you're a little bit worried about
that example actually well just en tiing
it to flow and every day yeah yeah but
it's fine it will do yeah so you know
but we could think about my just
reaching for my coffee cup yeah I want
to take a drink of coffee the the coffee
cup solicits my behavior it draws my
hand towards it so um so my actions are
kind of drawn from me in my forming an
equilibrium state with the the the
environment and so in our in our work
with Yer and Eric we Tred to argue that
this tending towards an optimal grip can
be thought of as a consequence of uh of
what we were then calling variational
free energy minimization and now I think
since then know that that paper was
written in 2016 so the field has moved
on
enormously now we would think about that
those sorts of examples of tending
towards a good grip tending towards an
improved grip in terms of expected free
energy
minimization um but the idea there was
that that this kind of tending towards
the right sort of optimal relationship
with the environment uh is a consequence
of uh what we can model in terms of free
energy
minimization um now is that
representational well I've been saying
no it's not because the the the
generative model is is not something
that the organism has it's something
that the organism embodies right we can
think about what are the Dynamics that
the organism
instantiates and do we need to bring in
content uh uh or representations to
uh explain the states that the the
internal states that the organism
instantiates and that's where I think
you know the idea of inactive active
inference sorry inactive inference that
ramstead and uh Carl and Michael
introduced in their adaptive Behavior
paper um Carl talks about
embodied uh inference sometimes these
are all ways of unpacking what how
active inference might be understood
where you think no the organism is a
model and so it doesn't need to
represent anything it can sure it can
just be thought of in terms of uh states
that carry Shannon information about the
world where that's non
semantic and so that's one thing I want
to say that the translation from the
ready to hand via this notion of
solicitation tending towards an optimal
grip those Notions can be un
unpacked uh in a way that um maybe we
can carry ize in terms of
content content to be motor
intentionality as Mel Ponte was
describing it or compartment towards the
ready to hand as heiger would describe
it yeah if that's what you're calling
content fine yes it's okay to talk about
content here why because the content
here is traced back in the end to
something that we can describe in lived
experience
sure I wouldn't call it
representational and nor would I call it
like semantic meaning right draus
wouldn't either uh those satisfaction
conditions Max does so Maxwell has this
paper where it's he's trying to give an
account with inis actually strangely
inis is like a a nonrepresentational
inactive theorist but they have this
paper together where they try to give a
formal semantics
for they try to derive a formal
semantics ICS out of um basian mechanics
yes and know that formal semantics if
you think you can get formal semantics
out of basian mechanics I think that
that's really a a representationalist
program that you're on there sure thing
they do is kind of it goes into this
instrumentalist realist thing again that
you've talked about before yes so
there's there's a little bit of as if
stuff going on or looks like you got to
read you got to read carefully you got
to read through the lines yeah um so
perhaps if you go instrumentalist here
then you can hold on to in's kind of
sure inactive take on where
representations come from that they only
come from practices they're not
something that you find or they come
from the science of making models so
scientists make models those models can
then be interpreted instrumentally as uh
useful tools for representing Dynamics
and so on so you can start to think
think of where representations come in
through scientific practices or without
thinking that the brain is is doing uh
operations over semantic bearing content
bearing States sure I mean I I still
find it a slight challenge that
distinction because I think there's a
question about well how does how does
public language become exapted into uh
internal language such that you can even
speak of internal representations but I
think that's a separate question
um I think the thing to say there as
well and this is something I've argued
with with Eric as well that if you think
that that the generative model is
non-representational it doesn't thereby
become representational just through a
process of uh reenacting or
reusing uh states that are uh content
bearing like uh when we engage in inner
speech and we make use of right language
to think with that's very much a
phenomenological experience that we have
of thinking in
language um but we shouldn't think uh
infer from that that when we're
explaining inner speech in terms of
neural
processes then um there's inference over
semantic bearing States going on
um
the so yes
yeah I
in have the issue separating those
phenomenal and content but maybe that's
just
me there's the modeling which is uh
something that can be characterized in
purely
mathematical uh statistical terms just
in terms of Shannon
information and then there's the
interpretation the gloss that we give of
the model as
scientists where we
may be able to interpret what we're
modeling in terms of meaning and
representation but that's something that
we're doing as scientists who are making
use of representations to interpret
their
models and yet there is still unless
you're an Illusionist about the whole
thing phenomenal
experience and so I find it difficult
just personally to to separate content
from phenomenal
experience
so yes that's what I was arguing as well
and trying to connect to motor
intentionality in in phenomenology
in or to the ready to hand okay dealings
with the ready to hand so yeah okay okay
that okay I see that okay those are
those are Notions of intentionality and
content and meaning yes without without
truth and accuracy being built in
yeah and they're they're not they're
descriptions of lived experience of
human beings uh so uh when we're
describing lived experience I agree it
makes total sense to bring in the notion
of intentionality as a structure of
lived
experience then if we try to read that
back into what we're modeling when we
use a generative model or um or into the
target system that we're modeling the
brain yes then there's a an extra move
that's being made there that we can go
from the notion of intentionality as
it's used to understand lived
experience to whatever we're doing as
scientists when we use a a
Model Model A Target system the brain so
there are three things there there's
lived experience there's the model and
the basian beliefs that we use to uh to
write down a generative model and then
there's the target system the brain that
we're using the generative model to uh
to make inferences about in the end um
and uh where do we bring in
intentionality well for me only in lived
experience and then we can use the model
the basian beliefs basian mechanics to
uh explain in the terms of cognitive
neuroscientists in the terms of
cognitive Neuroscience sorry uh lived
experience that's the generative passage
from phenomenology to cognitive
Neuroscience that's made possible by
basian mechanics but we shouldn't think
that then we're going to read back
straight from the
phenomenology uh intentionality into the
basian mechanics basian mechanics is
just mathematics and
statistics yes
explains what's described in
phenomenology because of the generative
passage but we need to be careful not to
just conflate the two and mash the two
together they're not the same thing pH
mechanics and intentionality no it's a
very useful
disambiguation I guess the the only
question that well one of the only
questions that comes one of the
questions that comes to mind because I
have plenty uh is about perception
because perception is cast
as resulted again it's quite it's not
particularly well sketched out but
resulting from basum mechanics in the
sense that perceptual adequacy is just
the minimization of the KO Divergence of
the recognition density and the true
posterior so this leads us quite nicely
into affordances because you have in
your 2014 paper you have I believe the
section is called afford affordances for
higher cognition and you talk about this
example of a nettle and mint leaves
which I would like to read out because I
think it would be a very useful framing
so you say
um so you quote Gibbs who says that the
affordances of human behavior are
staggering because it's in the whole
domain of social significance and then
you give this example you say for
instance when we are out looking for
mint leafes to make mint tea and a
friend incorrectly reaches for a nettle
we can stop him or her by making the
Judgment that is not a mint leaf that is
a nettle in doing so we are skillfully
engaging with the affordances the nettle
Leaf has in our form of life the leaf of
fors judging correctly that it is a
nettle in our form of life you see for
me for me I just cast that as a that
just for me is just well one person's
model is perceptually adequate and the
others isn't and for me that's pure
basian mechanics about the reduction of
the K Divergence but that yields that
doesn't necessarily yield me an
affordance in terms of public language
use it just yields
perception so maybe you could explain
because people might hear that and go
well I don't think that the seeing of
the uh nettle is in and of itself
encapsulated in the notion of an
affordance to inform your friend that
it's a
netal rather this is just perception
right and the role of perception is
purely just to achieve what I've been
calling descriptive adequacy whereas
action the maximization of model
evidence is normatively gives us
normative viability normative uh yeah
normative explanations so it seems to me
that you're kind of slotting perception
into um norms
and in some sense the maximization of
model evidence I.E I need to be a good
social actor in this
situation well one one thing that's
important about that example is that
it's supposed to be an example of
discursive uh thought so the person
judges that's not a uh a nettle
sorry Leaf yeah that's not a
a nettle that's a mint leaf or is it the
other way around I can't remember no
it's not a n it's not a mint leaf it's a
nettle but the point is that it's a it's
a demonstrative judgment that's being
made a judgment about the the type of
leaf that the person's just picked so
there's a there's a perceptual
categorization going on that might make
it look like it's just like a a
perceptual uh phenomena that's being
described here but it was being
introduced as a an example of
perceptions serving as a a reason for
making a judgment uh a particular kind
of demonstrative judgment uh about the
the type of leaf that you're looking for
and whether this is that type of leaf or
not uh so uh uh it was being given as an
example of higher cognition because uh
people think that higher cognition is
reason responsive so you're in the space
of reasons you're not just in the space
of causes anymore to use u a distinction
from Wilfred Sal
um so if you can make this kind of
demonstrative judgment based on your
perception that's because you're you're
responsive to what the reasons are
here uh so there's a kind of rationality
in play in this example of
perception um and then the question is
well can you you were pushing the idea
well it's just about the uh the basian
mechanics this kind of using of
perception to make judgment
um and there I think we need to be
careful to distinguish personal level
explanation which is explanation in
terms of reasons from subpersonal
processes which are being described by
basian
mechanics uh where uh the inferential
processes here are are supposed to be
just a matter of um mechanics just a
matter of basian mechanics sure um and
we want to in the end connect up what
we're appealing to in our personal level
explanations this is the bridging idea
uh with what can be described
subpersonal in terms of basian
mechanics but how do you go from the
personal level explanation which is
reason giving kind of explanations to
subpersonal
explanation uh there's an interface
problem as it's sometimes called here
how do you get your reasons to interface
with causes which is what you're
interested in when you're thinking about
basian
mechanics and I I think what you were
doing was saying well you were missing
that there's an
interface uh that we need here that
allows us to move from U personal level
explanations to subpersonal explanations
and we shouldn't lose that interface no
no I agree with that uh I I I've been
I've said on paper that I think there is
an issue how perception let's say just
gets chucked out of ko divergences I
that's an issue I'm not denying that I
guess my question here was here so going
back to the phenomenology uh discussions
again uh the way I was we were thinking
about this was well there's the kind of
intentionality that perception has where
uh that can be thought of just in terms
of U what H called passive and active
synthesis so there's a kind of
Constitution that we can appeal to at
work in perception that is uh pre-
predicative comes before any categories
are introduced and then there's um a
kind of intentionality which is
distinctive of thought and judgment
where where that is uh predicative it's
categorized so you're bringing in some
kind of subject toob distinction you're
dealing with the present at hand yeah um
and this example was supposed to be like
an example of that moves from the ready
to hand to the present at hand and
because there's some sort of breakdown
that happens there's a mistake that's
made um that gets corrected and that
pushes you to start to think and make
judgments uh so you're not any longer
dealing with just being drawn by well
actually we want to say you are because
we bring in this idea of affordances
that come from language but um but
what's important is that we're dealing
with a with a discursive propositional
predicative form of intentionality
in the Judgment that's being made here
not just a pre-
predicative subject objectless form of
intentionality sure yeah I guess I guess
my part of my point
was uh we have to integrate the ready
toh handedness form of intentionality
with the present at handedness
intentionality abely yeah and I I I
think like maybe one reading of this
would just be like oh we're just
skipping over the fact that there's some
uh uh concept free perception going on
in the first place and I just wanted to
get clarity that that's not what you're
saying right there is still the
perceptual act prior to the
categorization that language grants
us so there's there's like I agree with
you that we need uh some way of
integrating the ready to hand and the
present to hand that's what you just
said that's absolutely right that takes
us back to this question of higher and
lower cognition um how we want to call
into question that distinction in the
end um so you could think there's still
a distinction to be made here so looking
at the paper by Andrew ceran and yakob
Hoy and Giovani pulo yeah they have this
beautiful picture where you can go from
um homeostasis to allostasis to planning
deep temporal models and you might think
that underwrites a a distinct iction
between higher cognition which is where
you find planning and deep temporal
models and lower cognition where it's
just about homeostasis or about
chemotaxis like in the shanson
colleagues model of
chemotaxis so there's this like
differentiation that you get where
higher cognition emerges in in these
deep temporal
models um yes and what we want to say is
well that's a kind of approach where you
try to get to higher cognition
vertically by building up from um lower
cognition Mia homeostasis to higher
cognition deep active
inference uh paramet deep parametric
active inference as L saned Smith calls
it quite yeah yeah now we want to do
something that's different from that
which is to
horizontalization instead of trying to
build up to higher cognition vertically
in the generative models through
temporal depth we want to look at the
Horizon uh in which we engage with the
environment and think that uh spatially
and
temporally there can be more or less
distal engagements with the environment
that are made possible by us being uh by
our cultural practices so this go back
to where we actually started on the
question of cultural ecosystems Niche
construction and how um once we have in
view the idea that the environment
predicts agents as much as agents
predict the environment then we can
start to have a picture where instead of
thinking of uh temporal depth as coming
from um the hierarchy in the Deep
temporal generative model we can think
of temporal depth as coming from the
ecosystems in which we're
situated um and the way that those
ecosystems make possible dealing with
distal uh states of Affairs that are
currently absent from us that's what I
think we get from language from uh being
able
to um engage in propositional type uh
reasoning reason in that where we're
using predicative forms of
intentionality this is how you sort of
end up swallowing up yeah to to do um
perceptual judgment to do thinking about
what is currently absent um dealing with
the distal and so on where people
normally bring in
representations yeah so this is how you
swallow up if you pardon the pun uh
representation hungry cognition uh um
whereby you dis you sort of refute
offline cognition as being distinct but
rather this quote more complex form of
coordinating nested states of action
Readiness and activities to multiple
relevant affordances such a process is
complex because of the nesting of the
activities and their increasing reach
through time which I guess gives us well
at least your answer to Shapiro's uh
challenge which is how is not going to
be convinced by that I mean you already
said well yes natural signs don't
explain how you can navigate from
Madison to wherever yes I guess my
question here is why can't we have both
and so what I mean by that is you also
give another example from Shapiro
reenacting his past experiences going to
his house his former house in New Jersey
and you say that you know him pretending
to engage in those activities of being
there is in itself a Act of coordinating
to multiple relevant affordances
but my question is why can't we H why
can't we sort of have our cake and eat
it too in the sense that we can we can
accept that and we can accept that when
I'm trying to get my train from or my
plane from Madison to Cologne uh that's
me reacting to the affordance of going
to cologne and what that might afford me
why can't we also say that to even kick
off that process I have this kind of
online offline representation which
frames my nested activities I want to go
to
Cologne or are we or or is that
permitted because you want to reframe
representation Hungary cognition you you
say you know you give the quote
possibility of a positive alternative
namely whether the representation hungry
cognition might be achieved by other
means by for example skillfully
coordinated complexly structured nested
activities to multiple affordances such
that episodic memory imagining can be
given in these terms what I just don't
see why we can't have have both we had
the benefits of saying okay these are
representational so they include content
they include public language or private
language in this case and also there a
response to affordances why do we need
one rather than the
other
um so it goes back to a number of things
that we've been talking about already so
one is where does intentionality
originate from uh where does content
meaning originate from from and so yeah
uh I I've been contending that uh that
the source of intentionality is lived
experience um sure so the reason why I
want to appeal to uh practices in the
form of life uh like how language is
used within communities following a
vicentini model um is because that
traces meaning back to uh something
human to to uh to what human beings do
when they are speakers of uh English
so um what they are able to do then is
to articulate certain thoughts but
they're also able to um to revisit past
experiences uh by constructing
narratives about those past experiences
so uh that connects us to the The
Narrative topic again um and I think the
way that you were describing things was
to to suggest that narratives can be
modeled at the higher layers of these
deep temporal models that's absolutely
right they can be modeled in that way um
but does that mean then that that the
narratives just are uh the uh processes
processes of inference that take place
within these deep temporal models and
that's where I I would say no we
shouldn't make an identity between the
narrative and the uh and what we're
modeling using a model because the the
modeling practice is being done by a
scientist yeah and those models that the
scientist is constructing are what we
use then to explain some Target
phenomena which is the the cognitive
process of constructing
narratives um but can also be understood
in terms of the link the actions of uh
Norm normatively regulating your
linguistic behaviors so that they fit
with how other speakers of your language
behave um that's something which is very
much a cultural communal
activity um
so uh yes generative models capture
these processes they give us ways of
explaining them in the terms of the free
energy principle and cognitive
Neuroscience um should we then take the
phenomena that we're modeling to be
nothing over and above uh what can be
modeled using these generative processes
so we simply
identify the behaviors of constructing
narratives thinking about our past
experiences being a master of linguistic
practices uh can we just identify those
behaviors with what we're modeling when
we use generative models that's where I
say no because there's a lot more to um
the linguis
behaviors uh there are the practices the
what people do when they belong to
communities now
interestingly and this connects to where
we started from those practices and um
communal behaviors can also be modeled
using uh basian mechanics where we think
that the system now is is a collective
system that has maybe collective
intelligence and is made up of lots of
interacting agents
uh so we can also model that system
using basian mechanics but should we
then say that the collective system just
is uh a free energy
minimizer uh no because the S the target
system here is one that can also be
described by doing social science by
doing Linguistics um it can be described
using lots of different explanatory
Frameworks and all of those planetary
Frameworks can be made
to um Bridge can be bridged to from
basian mechanics that's super
interesting but we shouldn't then try to
do a reduction of all of these other
explanations to basian
mechanics um so what I'm resisting here
is a kind of
reductionism uh where everything can
just be taken back to physics again sure
I want to say no there are social
dynamics cultural dynamics that uh where
we need the tools of social science
where we need to do ethnography for
instance or anthropology or where we
need to do phenomenology to understands
these Dynamics and and those also give
us very good ways of interpreting and
understanding what human beings are
doing as
agents
yes yeah I I I didn't mean I I don't
think it's a reductive claim the
phenomenal the relationship between the
phenomenal and the physics um where I've
written about it I've used words like
emergent or causally Downstream from and
I know these are problematic words and
whether it's supervenient or not these
are obviously very tricky and
philosophically um deep questions I
guess my my only Point here about
was if it it doesn't need to be
reductive to say that representations at
least in this uh episodic memory
reimagining might have a role or may
play a part I'm not saying it's the
whole picture I'm not saying that it
replaces the basian mechanics I think
representations do play a role in
episodic memory because there are forms
of episodic memory which are are such
that we can articulate and we can
express linguistically what we're
remembering and that's process of of
putting it into words of articulating it
is part of the con construction the
Reconstruction of that memory okay yeah
that's that's exact yeah that's exactly
right so so then the qu my question
really was why are we considering this a
you you posit the uh the framing of
offline representations as nested
activities governed by the affordances
that the environment grants us as a
positive alternative to representation
hungry cognition but it sounds like
you're also permitting there to be some
representational schema in place so yeah
the differences that we don't think of
the the representations as something
that's part of the information
processing but uh representations get
involved but not not via the generative
model because the generative model for
us is just is just a mathematical model
it's just pure statistics it's not
bringing in and you can then give
interpretations of that statistics using
constructs like basian belief and
inference over beliefs and inference of
posterior and so on but that's all a
gloss on something that is just
mathematics and statistics so where do
the representations come in when we're
trying to understand and explain in
terms of cognitive Neuroscience episodic
memory they don't come in through the
brain they come in through the coupling
between the agent and an environment
that is structured by social cultural
linguistic practices so we talk about
affordances in our more recent workers
in
languaged Andy Clark talks about
material symbols he has very interesting
work with um um trying to think of the
name the guy's name Gary lupian about
how U material symbols for instance can
sculpt Precision
expectations um but they're doing that
work not uh internally but uh as
material symbols that are uh in the
environment that are situated in the
environment so this example of language
sculpting attention sculpting Precision
is an example of a looping through the
world where the material symbols are
being taken up and included in the um in
the Precision estimation process in the
sculpting of precision as something that
is located in the environment something
where the agent is coupling with a with
an environmental structure in this case
the material symbols yeah that that that
makes it a lot clearer for me I guess
the question that going back to
Shapiro's episodic memory
imagining
so what would that look like in this
kind of worldly Loop so he so just to
provide the example he imagines going
back to his family parent house in in
New Jersey and he's say how on Earth
could that be you know how on Earth can
that be representation free but you're
not saying that's representation fre
you're saying it's just that that
representation is yielded from the ACT
uh the agent Arena relationship and it's
not actually part of the basian
mechanics okay but what does what what
does that mean for this the basian
mechanics because I want the basian
mechanics story to apply to Extended
cognitive systems as well sure sure it's
just internal to the brain anymore the
part of this that's getting the
representations involved is the coupling
with uh representational practices so
being a language speaker who can uh can
articulate and put into words uh a past
experience like the um the poster that
was hanging on your bedroom wall as a
child yes Jimmy Andre being able to
remember that poster is something that
you can do because you're a language
speaker who can uh can describe can make
sense of linguistically past experiences
that you had is it wrong to say that
just because that that capacity is
scaffolded from the my development and
the culture from which I've been in
which I've been raised that that hasn't
become
internalized is it or you say are you
permitting that because you're saying
it's not in the brain I mean my
intuition is telling me that fine like
language didn't I mean unless you know
we're not going to go into in nativism
and chompsky but like because it's not
really that relevant but fine language
comes from uh exposure to data and
societal norms and so on but at a
certain point I can use
language in the absence of social
contexts uh in ter like in the case of
my em imagining Shapiro's em imagining
so it seems like in that case it has
been internalized to some degree it's
just that it it
was the the presence of a previous
social Dynamic was
necessary for its
internalization MH yeah so that's really
interesting and the the key question
there is how to think about what
internalization means exactly in the
case of episodic
imagining um so uh in keeping with the
ecological inactive approach uh what we
what we try to do is say well what
conceptual framework do you need for
making sense of uh episodic imagining in
terms of uh basian
mechanics so uh is it a representational
conceptual framework or can we instead
use the uh the tools of ecological
inactive cognitive science the what we
call the skilled intentionality
framework to make sense of um the basian
mechanics that's involved in in in that
example of episodic
imagining um and we would argue that uh
you can make sense of What's Happen
happening in that case by thinking of it
not vertically I.E looking at the top
layers of the generative model and then
saying that's where episodic imagining
happens it happens in a kind of mental
time travel that is made possible by
Deep active inference but instead
thinking that the cognitive system here
is an agent environment system so uh
episodic imagining internalization of
linguistic abilities is a matter of
skills that you have as a as a language
user and those skills are uh are then
well the kind of meaning that's involved
here is accounted for in terms of
responsiveness to affordances so um this
all just sounds very philosophical and
not interesting to scientists so I'm not
sure how much your your listeners are
going to get out oh they're they're
philosophers they they love it um I mean
there's yeah to go to agent environment
system and and to try to understand
um horizontally in terms of the Dynamics
within the agent environment system what
could be going on when somebody can
revisit their past experiences and and
construct that kind of experience of the
poster on their wall uh so horizontally
what's going on there we think is that
you you're using your skills as a
language user um so as a a master of
English I can then um make sense of
my uh past
experiences um and and and interpret
them as the experiences of the this
poster of Jimmy Henrik let say yeah yeah
oh okay cultural stuff that's packed
into that yes and that that stems from
our skills as speakers of a language
sure okay to cap off this profound
conversation into affordances which I'm
sure has taken many people into the
weeds they probably us talking about it
I guess the question is the overarching
question therefore is so these
representational states are scaffold
yielded from language learning in a in a
cultural setting in terms of the actual
act therefore of
reimagining are is is the presence of
those do the presence of those
representations have a causal
role or are they just epip phenomenal
over the um the affordance
exploitation ah but the representations
just are affordances for us so now we
try to have an ecology a cultural
ecosystem that is populated by uh
affordances that that grow out
of our uh linguistic practices and so um
so the representation external
representations we think there there are
no internal mental representations
because um those are scientific
constructs yeah I an internal mental
representation that require you to be
able to solve this hard problem of
content that we were talking about
earlier on
yeah um we don't think that
representations are not real there are
real representations but they're just
not internal mental representations
they're not internal to the brain they
come from our cultural systems like our
linguistic practices our systems of
making pictures and images and
diagrams and we couple to those
practices as participants in those
practices and that's what allows us to
engage in uh in representational style
cognition by making use of these
external resources in our
environment okay and I guess the
people's worry might be the sort of
standard objection that this position
means that affordances can't have any
objective
quality which undermines Gibson's
original realism but I believe you have
a response to that in terms of the fact
that we also have to take in the
material reality of the affordances to
into account not only our sociocultural
practices again the paper the 2014
paper's cracking so everyone can just go
there um I mean how long have we been
going for 2 hours and 5 minutes okay
we'll wrap up in a bit in a sec there's
so many things I want to ask about um we
didn't even really touch you can you can
like figure it out in the editing right
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah it's all it's
all in the editing in the end I don't
edit them that much
um I do want to
so there's there's a paper that you have
about
mindness so about self-modeling and
mindness um which I thought was really
interesting as I've say I'm F this is
slightly further down on your Google
Scholar but I saw it and I thought I
have to have a bit of that because I
love the self modeling is entirely what
I'm fixated on the moment not entirely
and you
say in line with the arguments of the
phenomenologist I will claim that every
feeling must be felt by someone it must
have mindness built into it if it is to
feel a particular
way um some people might go well I
thought that annel Seth and absen airus
said that mindness came from inter
receptive inference and that is the sort
of seat of the so-called minimal
phenomenal self and if that disbands so
does the notion that the experiences the
feelings the affect I have of mine um
maybe it's worth
just separating your perspective or your
position from
theirs yeah so this goes back to again
generative passage between phenomenology
and uh and free energy principle
cognitive
Neuroscience because the the mindness
construct is a phenomenological
construct it's describing a structure of
um of
Consciousness whereby every conscious
state is
also experienced at the same time as it
is an
experience mindness is captured ing the
the
relationality uh that is part of the the
experience whereby it's an experience of
mine or yours it's sometimes this is
called sense of
ownership um that each experience is
owned by a
subject um and then when you have
phenomenal like depersonalization or
yeah uh
derealization uh that can be thought of
in terms of uh a loss of this experience
of uh of mindness we can debate whether
that is entirely lost or not so Anna
chica says it's not it's just Disturbed
in some way so there's still this
phenomenological structure that's
present but the phenomena of
depersonalization
derealization is a a disturbance of that
structure of experience and I think
that's right um so then what we need to
try to do is to uh to take the
phenomenological structure and and
Bridge to how we could think about that
in in terms of um active inference um
and that's where the idea of
interceptive inference or multisensory
integration understood in terms of um
integrating interceptive predictions
with
extracephalic that we can use to build
that bridge from the phenomenology the
idea of mindness as a phenomenological
structure to cognitive
Neuroscience okay so okay so so yeah
Anna doesn't say that it uh completely
disbands the uh sense of ownership I
don't know if you've read George Dean's
paper on well he's got two papers
wonderful one on derealization the other
on
psychics yeah self dissolution he goes a
bit further and I make this point at the
end of my paper that I think they're
talking about two separate parts of the
D realization process and I think Anna's
is just a bit more moderate whereas
George's is a bit more severe um it's a
good good difference that you pick up on
there that's that's definitely a a a uh
Divergence an interesting Divergence
just talking well in my from I think
it's very explicable that Divergence but
I think they're just talking about two
different phenomenological States but
George would
say she would be a really good guest she
yes well yeah I've spoken to her plenty
of times I think yeah I think she she
might well be coming on um but I guess
the question here is okay so I'm from
the school of people who say well
mindness is emerging from the
computational processes it's emerging
from the inter receptive inferences from
the integration the uh the multisensory
integration so what that means is that
if that breaks so for example George
gives example of torture so and I
mentioned this to Chris as well that if
you're in a torture chamber um you're
going to be very unlikely to be able to
succeed in suppressing inter receptive
prediction error and torture is a very
reliable instigator of
depersonalization but you but there are
still experiences there are still
feelings but the sense of ownership has
gone but you said I will claim that
every feeling must be felt by
someone so who are those feelings being
felt
by so what's lost is the transparency in
that case so um
ordinarily our uh our sense of mindness
the experential self is not something
that gets in the way something that
comes conspicuous in our experiences
rather transparent we look through it to
the Wells and that notion of
transparency is then modeled using uh uh
dis attending sensory attenuation Thomas
metzinger all that yeah yeah so uh what
happens in the in the torture example I
think is that the um
that
uh
your your what would normally be
transparent becomes
opaque and uh then becomes very
conspicuous to you and and your uh way
of
um uh dealing with the
uh prediction errors that come with a
pain experience and we've done some work
on pain is um is by uh dissociating from
it and
so okay that's interesting so it's yes I
mean people do talk about derealization
for example as this kind of bubble wrap
um that's there as a function to
dissociate from Pain and from the
anxiety of being eaten by a tiger or
whatever in the savannah um so okay
that's it's a kind of numbing of the
pain the so you're arguing that the
minus is still there it's just somewhat
clouded by this objectification or uh
opacity of what normally would be
transparent so go back to melon's
example of the two hands touching which
he uses to illustrate how the body is
both object and a subject of
experience and ordinarily there's this
what he calls a kaym so an intertwining
of the subjects and the objects in the
body um and what happens in um
depersonalization derealization is then
is that that this intertwining of
subject and object now breaks down you
have now a a kind of distancing of the
subject from their body um and that's NE
necessary in the torture example U it's
necessary to in some way disidentify
with the pain experiences to treat them
as some some kind of objects that
separate from you uh if you to be able
to to deal with the pain uh so the
derealization is a kind of adaptive
response to what would otherwise be
overwhelming where you can you can gain
a distance from it and relate to it as
as if it were not you that this was
happening to as if it were an object
that was separate from
you this is this is this is very much
Anna's account um and it feeds into this
notion of kind of hyper Precision over
um beliefs about the self model which
leads to this kind of dissociation but
again like the way that I was writing
about it was not only that but also what
um Dean and colleagues spoke about in
2020 which is they use this quote from a
writer called Loft House 2014
saying the first time I remember feeling
like the first time I can remember
feeling like I didn't exist I was 15 I
was sitting on a train and all of a
sudden I felt like I'd been dropped into
someone else's bodies my memories
experiences and feelings uh and feelings
the things that make up my intrinsic
sense of meanness projected across my
mind like
fantasmagoria but I felt like they
belong to someone else like I was
experiencing life in the third person so
this seems slightly
different but I think the key thing to
pull out from that quote is I felt like
like these experiences belong to
somebody else that I felt there is still
the presence of mindness so it's me that
this is happening to similarly in in
examples of ego dissolution that happen
yes that's what I was going to ask about
as well psychedelics that George talks
about in the losing ourselves paper and
also in the another paper about ego
dissolution I forget what it's called um
there are a couple on there yeah yeah uh
so you might think well ego dissolution
is a kind of egoless experience this is
how Raphael Miler describes uh ego
dissolution in in extreme examples that
there's just this complete uh loss of uh
of ego of self um but uh I I think
rather what happens in those examples is
that uh there's you that's undergoing
these these exp very strange experiences
um you still present as the subject of
them it's still U me that this is
happening to I've taken the Psychedelic
and now I'm undergoing this experience
of uh loss of boundary between me and
the world or this kind of feeling of
Union and connectedness with nature um
and that's an experience that I'm having
so it's there's there's still that
mindness that's part of the
experience um but there's something
that's lost as well which is this higher
narrative uh layer of the self so
instead of like identifying with who I
have been in the past and then uh that
ident identity um being brought into the
framing of my experience I think George
is right that there's this kind of loss
of temporal depth so yeah influence of
the narrative on your on your experience
of your of who you are at that moment is
now Stripped
Away but still what's in place is the
core or minimal self the
mindness and for you that's just
intrinsic to the experience yeah it's
part of the structure of the experience
it's a phenomenological structure
interesting described it called it
IP of course Disturbed in in uh
psychopathologies like schizophrenia or
uh depersonalization derealization
depression these are all disturbances of
the self yes of that Ipsy which is part
of our experiences our our perspective
on the wel so I guess my thinking here
is that where Maybe I'm Wrong that where
Dean and where I've divorced Dean
George's and Anna's
accounts there they can actually be tied
under the single banner
of uh
distancing opacity hyper precision over
self
models and so on not that Dean not that
George's account implies the
total uh dissolving of the self
model uh well you know there's there's
some debate about this isn't there about
whether the self model is entirely
dissolved or not and George I think just
talks about it in terms of this
shrinking of the temple depth uh this
dim diminu of the temporal
depth um so you you could ask well is
there still something that is left of
the self once that temporal depth is
lost yes um I would tend to think about
it in terms of different layers of the
self model um and the the temporal the
loss of temporal depth is describing the
The Narrative layer of the self model um
that could leave in place the
bodily
y core minimal self which is what is
accounting for
mindness and but it but but it isn't in
of itself according to
you um sufficient for mindness in the
sense that mindness is just part of the
structure of
experience so is what is there a
distinction here between mindness and
self modeling such that you could have
dissolved entirely dissolved self models
but you would still have experiences
that by necessity are POS are owned by
someone goes back to the same question
about the relationship between
phenomenology personal level explanation
subpersonal processes basian mechanics
and the way I think about that
relationship is using the idea of
generative passage from verella so
mindness and phenomenal selfhood I don't
think are um identical with um the
generative model and the processes that
are described using basian mechanics um
they they those processes
explain um in the sense of uh they give
us a model that would allow us to bridge
uh to
phenomenology but but they don't reduce
they don't you can't reduce the yes
first person experience which is where
we start from the livt experience to
what can then be described modeled in
third person terms using basian
mechanics but if I were to say that I
guess what I'm getting up to getting to
here is you could claim there have been
claims for example that interceptive
inference under writes the minimal self
model such that if inter receptive
inference falls apart if there's if it's
just completely unsuccessful such as in
the torture chamber the minimal self
model itself will dissolve if if you
just grant me that
uh causal
relationship well the construct of the
minimal self model is a a construct
introduced by met singer yeah in order
to um make sense of cognitive
neuroscientific models of uh uh of lived
experience of phenomenal selfhood and of
course met singer thinks that the we
should be strong realists about the
phenomenal self model as described in
cogn nitive neuroscience and and we
should say that that what we learn from
cognitive Neuroscience is there's no
self and that the that mindness is just
a a construct of the brain yes it's
hallucinated actually in the end a
controlled hallucination um yes and you
can but in the end you can lose it
entirely yeah because it depends on and
is identical with um inferential
processes that are taking place in brain
whereas my view is different from
Thomas's in that I don't start from
cognitive neuroscience and what can be
modeled within cognitive Neuroscience I
take as my starting point this is what
verella meant when he said um that
cognitive science should always uh go
back to find a way back to lived
experience because lived experience is
where we start from and he's what we
must always return to and this is from
um his paper on um
neurophenomenology so so the the idea
there is that what's basic what we start
from is lived
experience um and then we have to try to
find a way to explain that in the terms
of cognitive neuroscience and that's
what the phenomenal self model gives us
and what basium mechanics give us they
give us a way of explaining in
naturalistic cognitive science terms
what is described in phenomenology but
what's real what's most real here what
we start from is lived experience would
you say that thas says that the
phenomenal self model is identical to
the inferences that the brain makes or
is emergent over the inferential
mechanics that are occurring in the
brain as in one is causally related the
other one's an identity depends what you
mean by INF um emergent there so
emergence can be understood in like a a
weak sense of yeah um
epistemically we we can't really predict
from the the lower level the properties
that we find at the higher level because
of nonlinearity because of um uh know
because there's there's something um
nonadditive about the
causes uh that means you get something
qualitatively new once you move to the
higher level yes and that can just be
understood in a a purely epistemic way
or it can be understood ontologically
that there's something new that's
brought into
existence uh a self uh you get from U or
a phenomenal self model which is just a
construct of the brain but it's a higher
level construct that emerges out of
lower level processing as something
ontologically new um and then you could
say well what's the relationship between
the phenomenal self model and the
experience of being somebody or the
experience of
mindness and Thomas's answer to that
last question is that the experience of
being someone is an illusion it's a a
the outcome of um the phenomenal self-
modeling process which is in turn the
outcome of inference and basian modeling
he would now say I guess um
so um
emergence
to answer your question can be
understood in like a weak sense or it
can be understood in a stronger
ontological sense and the stronger
ontological notion doesn't decide in
favor of the reality of the self because
you could still believe that the
phenomenal self model is strongly
emergent even though in the end it's
just an inferential construct of the
brain and so whe whether you say
emergence gets you a real self or just
gets you uh an losery construct as
Thomas argues I think doesn't fall out
of the concept of emergence on its
own okay that's that's really that's
real food for thought um I'm G have to
want to differentiate out my position
and the position of other people that
are trying to do neurop phenomenology
from from Thomas's position because we
we
think I'll speak for myself I think that
the vellian project of generative
Passage
means that what's real here is um being
in the world or um lived experience the
body subject and and then the task for
for anyone that is doing fore cognition
that comes out of the inactive strand of
fore cognition is to try to build a
bridge back from lift experience to what
can be described
scientifically so thereby making room
for lived experience Within science and
that can then take a more elaborate form
like John V's project of not only just
trying to build room for lived
experience within cognitive science but
these rich Notions like wisdom and the
sacred and yeah meaning in life and so
on but yeah it's it's at least according
to
your the your own phenomenological Camp
I'm right to say that the reduction to
the science is a false move
yeah I take fore cognition to be
non-reductive and sometimes that that
non-reduction move is is cached out in
terms of a strong notion of emergence so
that connects to what I think you were
trying to do so Evan Thompson will talk
about
um neurophenomenology as committed to uh
circular causality where at the the
level of the higher levels that are to
do with consciousness and lived
experience loop back down and change the
yes the lower level
Dynamics so that's a a kind of downward
causation or a strong form of emergence
that he he he thinks you get from um
from neurodynamics from self
organization from autonomy which is
where we started from um so
neurophenomenology then would would get
you a kind of metaphysics where uh there
a strong form of
emergence and Consciousness can actually
make a difference to um neurodynamics to
yeah as a higher level property it can
loop back down and and change the faster
changing processes in the brain yes well
this this has its
resonance to use a Rel relevant term
with active
inference um but yeah as you say it does
there's this idea of enslaving and
synergetics and that Carl has been
influenced by it comes from Herman
harken where uh there's there's like
onsemble dynamics that unfolder over
slower time
scales that loop back and change the
faster time scales
so causation that's been describe there
just get away from the analytic
philosophy just more
colloquially would you ever use the term
self-modeling for you does it make does
it does it make sense in terms of the uh
phenomenological starting point to even
talk about self models or is it does it
does it make more sense to talk about
intentionality and mindness and so on so
I again we have this necessity to to
keep apart the phenomenology which we're
trying to bridge to where I think
Notions like mindness and intentionality
are have their home yeah and the the the
modeling that we're doing when we use
active inference models to
explain uh there I don't where we also
talk about models and um we talk about a
generative model and and we then give
intentional semantic glosses on that
generative model but that last move I I
resist making and I say know that
intentionality always belongs within
lived
experience which we can then explain
using basian mechanics which is
non-intentional
non-representational I me I meant more
maybe I should have said more this is
like
metacognition because metacognition in a
way is it feels like a form of
intentional self-modeling or
phenomological self- modeling in the
sense of in lived experience you are
reflecting on
yourself
yeah is that not a self model which is
grounded in phenomenological
intentionality so using uh Thomas's
framework we can talk about the
phenomenal self model and we can say
within that there's a minimal self and
then there's the four epistemic agent
model yeah yeah the epistemic agent
model so these these are all ways of
talking about the self model within uh
active
inference um and I don't of course I
don't deny that we can talk about the
self model there in fact I in the paper
you talked about I do something that no
one else has picked up on and no one
else seems to like which is to say that
all generative models are actually self
models because the what's being modeled
by a generative model is an agent uh so
going back to the uh the agent is a
model of its environment and theat
Theorem and so on and and the agent in
in active uh cognitive science in active
philosophy is uh a point of view a
perspective on the world relative to
which you can make sense of the world
and make distinctions between what's
good for me what's bad for me
and so uh I want to argue that um right
at the core of all generative modeling
because the generative model at least
when it's applied to life is the model
of an agent a minimal agent is a self-
model uh so generative models are always
self models I want to argue it's not
that there's some part of a a a
generative model at the higher layers of
it where we can start to say well that's
the self model or in interceptive
inference say and say that's the self
model I think
um mik Allen and and Manos Securus have
a beautiful figure actually where they
have like the self model right at the
core of uh of active inference and
that's to me is right that they talk
about the first prior yeah the body is
the first prior Yeah Anna Cher and and
um Catalina also talk about the the and
Manos also talk about the self as a
first prior but they understand the self
model here in a more relational ways
into subjective so thinking about
attachment Dynamics for instance but all
of that work for me indicates that you
can't really take the idea of the agent
as a model of its inv enironment without
thinking that the the model there is a
self model so I'm very serious I think
the self model construct is extremely
important in thinking about how the
agent could be a model of its
environment um but the move that Thomas
makes then of of just reducing the self
as a phenomenological experience to the
self modeling I want to resist because I
don't like his reductionism and I
certainly don't like his move of saying
the self doesn't exist self is not real
and I don't think Buddhism really uh
substantiates that idea and I don't
think uh cognitive science supports it
either so I would resist a kind of move
to a no self
Theory
okay I'm going to call I'm going to say
that that's that's good for me because
uh We've covered so much ground and we
could go on for hours more
but tired you're tired so well I just
there's so much to think about um you
know in my to be candid I mean I'm
coming out of the metser school which is
informed Act of
inference so it's difficult at a
personal level to real time shift one's
Paradigm because maybe some of the Bear
in mind that there's U there are other
ways of using active inference here that
don't necessarily leads to a no self
Theory and well yeah I
mean I I I I
wouldn't is there a difference between
the no self and the constructed
self uh yes and that you can think that
constructions are real U whereas Thomas
want to say no if the self is
constructed inferentially yeah then we
should infer from that that
that no one ever was or had a self yes
I've seen him say that yeah so I agree
that the self is a construct so Evan
Thompson what Evan says yeah yeah he has
this very nice idea in in his work on uh
on Eastern philosophy that he's why I am
not a Buddhist yeah where he thinks that
the self is a construct but the layers
of the self that construct the self come
from things like the body from our into
subjective relations like Katarina and
Manos aru from our uh being uh members
of a culture where other people can
understand us in a particular way so
then we can take on board how we're
perceived or understood by others so
these are all layers that lead to the
construction of the self um but we
shouldn't then infer that the self isn't
real just because it's constructed or no
one ever was or had a self
that just doesn't follow and I I don't
want to like go on the side of
instrumentalist here and say if it's a
modeling tool then what's being modeled
is not anything real right so Michael
and I have done work on this with Ian
Robertson where we say that that amounts
to making what we call the the
literalist fallacy so the fallacy of
thinking that in order for a model to be
a model of Something Real the model has
to be taken literally as describing what
is literally happening in the world and
we think that's not true you can be a
realist about these models without um
without thinking that what's being
described is something that's literally
real and so sure models involve you
making all kinds of imaginative leaps
from what your modeling to the Target
phenomena yeah that that that's really
useful I you know I feel like I've been
slightly converging on this in my own
thinking that there's
a something that I've been coming to
find is that there's a difference this
might be not entirely the same but it's
adjacent there's a difference between
maybe what the basian mechanics permits
and I use that word knowing that it's
probably the wrong word but permits in
terms of the
phenomenology and there's an actual but
there's a difference between that and
the actual phenomenology
itself and I think that might be akin to
yeah that's exactly what I'm saying so
there's the model that we use as
scientists and then there's the target
system that we're modeling which is the
system as just well phenomenologists
wouldn't call it a system but Liv the
experience as it's described which is
what we're trying to do and we're trying
to build this generative passage from
the modeling to
phenomenology um and those are different
one is the model the other is the target
of the model yeah yeah yeah yeah the
Target phology or it can be the brain
because these are both targets that
we're trying to use the generative
modeling to capture but the relationship
here is between the model and the target
system oh that's so useful that's so
useful again it's not helped by the fact
that it's called a phenomenal self model
is it I mean uh that's a way of really
deflating that
Gap but of course for
metzinger he does that for a good reason
because he thinks no one ever was or had
a self so all that is to the self is the
phenomenal self
model whereas I'm saying no
phenomenologically the self belongs in
phenomenology and it's real because
that's where it comes from but isn't it
a bit odd to call it a phenomenal self
model and then say there's nothing
there's no self given that it's
phenomenal does that not strike you as a
slight contradiction because we take
phenomenal the phenomenal reality to be
real in of itself regardless of how we
end up demarcating it and reifying it we
take lived experiences the stuff idea of
the ego Tunnel right so yeah and it's a
bit like the pl Plato's Cave
myth so yes the self appears to us and
it appears to be real but the argument
is then it's just an appearance it's
just a and where does that appearance
come from it comes from the construction
of this phenomenal self
model that's enough for
me that still seems to be like what
you're talking about in terms of
mindness subjectivity intentionality
which to me seem to be the things that
matter in the
end yeah interesting I think comes back
to is whether you're a physicalist or
not so if you if you think that reality
fundamentally is just what can be
described and explained by physics which
I think Thomas would in the end endorse
yes uh the phenomenal self model is
going to be reducible to um to
neurobiological processes and those are
going to In the End come back to
something physical whereas
phenomenologists are not physicalists
they're
non-reductive um yeah yeah yeah yeah
naturalists yeah yeah they try to have a
softer form of naturalism John fi talks
about Transcendent naturalism in some of
his work that's a that's because he has
this he has in view uh trying to get to
the wisdom traditions in the end from
these ideas but um but these softer
forms of naturalism I think are alive
possibilities for us as well when we're
using active inference and the the free
energy principle we don't have to be
physicalists whereas Alex yakob Hoy you
know they're they're long time on uh
card holding
physicalists um and the free energy
principle goes nicely with physicalism
because there's so many of these ideas
are coming from physics and um so you
might think well it follows from where
all of these ideas are being drawn from
that we can we should end up being
physicalists about uh anything that's
described in phenomenology which means
being reductionists but I just don't
think that that's right and so so going
forward how how would well not going
forward in your present work and past
work and forward work how would you talk
what words would one use to talk about
bridging this Gap because we want to
keep the basing mechanics and we want to
keep the phenomenology and we want to
find an explanation that's
non-reductive so what is the what what
you know this is taking me back to
philosophy when I was at school what are
the relations that we're trying to
describe here are these causal relations
are these like are these you know
they're not epip phenomenal but what so
how how what's the best way of talking
about them from your
perspective uh well uh I see myself as
doing neurop
phenomenology so what that means is that
um I think there's a
necessity when we're
explaining phenomena that ATT tied to a
lived experience like Consciousness the
self and disturbances that can happen in
mental illness uh of making reference to
first second person experience and and
that then means
using um methods for studying first
person experience
like uh phenomenology but also uh
contemplative methods like meditation
mindfulness because they involve
something that is akin to uh the
phenomenological reduction as it was
practiced by phenomenology so what we
then need to try to do is to find ways
of bridging between what can be
described in first person terms and what
can be described third person what's the
relationship between those well a
reductionist would say that the first
person reduces to the third person
whereas uh I try to uh have a
metaphysics where uh it's
non-reductive so what does that look
like well I don't think there's anything
outside of science that we're dealing
with here so there nothing like
metaphysically spooky being introduced
here I wouldn't want to say but we need
a more relaxed
naturalism um what is the metaphysics of
that going to involve well it involves
having a richer notion of causality for
instance than just efficient causality
because we're thinking about
self-organizing systems now so we need
to have what uh
Al Alicia wero in her
book um context matters for everything
or something right constraints yeah
enabling constraints yeah yeah so we
need that we need a notion of enabling
constraints for instance here um we need
self-organization we need to have a kind
of teleology here so in discussions of
the free energy principle people
sometimes wonder about um what's the
reality of uh
of the what Spinosa called the
canus is part of what we're looking at
when we try to model agents as free
energy minimizing systems and axol said
no it's not because um the existence of
the agent is a consequence of free
energy minimization it's not you don't
get an explanation of why agents exist
out of free energy
minimization and I want to say something
different from Axel there that um that
living systems do indeed have this drive
to maintain themselves this canatas so
the metaphysics that we need here is
something that looks a lot like
Spinoza's metaphysics that you've got a
you've got a
substance um I I don't really like
substance talks or that part of ity and
resist and go to processes but sure but
you do need this idea of a canus I think
um in accounting for what makes the
difference between a pebble and a living
system
say
and we can make sense of in terms of
free energy minimization as well so the
metaphysics that comes out of this is
not physicalist metaphysics it's
something that has room for there being
a difference between living systems and
Pebbles um and that we can make sense of
Beyond just a physics in terms of Basi
and mechanics so look at the paper about
strange particles for instance yeah so
um and look at the work that Michael and
I did about the difference between mere
active inference and adaptive active
inference and and there's there's an
account there a princip account that
comes out of active inference about the
difference
between a mere physical system and a
living system a biological agent this
goes Loops back to where we started with
a yeah of course of course I'm just so
aware that Carl would just say well this
is this is just and I'm using his hand
signals uh you know this is the depth of
temporal
planning that's again what you're saying
difference yeah but you're saying that's
that's the basian mechanics but you
that's not everything there's a
non-reductive phenomenology on top of
it yeah so I do want to say that that uh
that it isn't just about the the
temporal depth of the generative model
that's difference between the a being
that has a canus a drive to maintain
itself and and uh yeah because the model
here is just a model of that kind of
thing that kind of being yeah yeah yeah
yeah oh Julian gosh I've learned so much
I thought I came in knowing roughly what
I was talking about and I've left ever
so confused and in doubt of myself but
nonetheless it's been wonderful and or
inspiring and Incredibly informative
should do to you they should just leave
you in a a bit of a confused state where
you then try sort through your
confusions and make sense of them and no
no not at all it's been incredibly
useful I feel like I've kind of um
cheated my way six months ahead of my
education in in three hours so that's no
bad thing it's it's no just super
informative um what can people look
forward to in terms of your upcoming
work yeah so something we didn't get to
talk about at all which is a shame is
the work we've been doing on play and
playfulness yes I know yes yeah a
Dynamics aerodynamics came up very
briefly so I've been working with Mark
Miller and in uh arus University with uh
Mark Anderson there um we've been
developing ideas around uh why it's fun
and and pleasurable to learn through
play activities um so together with Mark
Anderson we have a paper that's uh
now under revision with topics in
cognitive science and in a special issue
about developments of development of
models of the world um and we talk about
the contribution of play to uh in child
development in that paper using the our
ideas about aerodynamics and carrying on
our account of why it's fun to learn
through uh play yes so that's one of the
things that we're working on um and then
together with my colleague Daman Denise
here in Amsterdam we're starting a new
center on uh uh this interface between
Psychiatry Psychotherapy and philosophy
fantastic my work as part of that will
be using active inference to try to uh
understand Psychotherapy say in the
context of psychedelic Psychotherapy for
instance so I'm doing work on
psychedelics that come out of that but
also trying to apply active inference to
to make make sense of um mental illness
more generally and finally know how
things can go well for people so that's
the work that I've been doing with Mark
Miller on uh well-being and meaning in
life um that's going to continue to be a
strand of research to uh to try to make
sense of how uh how people can be happy
and be well using these tools of uh of
active inference wonderful well I'm
gonna need to go take a nap because I've
had my worldview just demolished and I
didn't even know that it was problematic
but it's fine um I'm sure we'll stay in
touch um I'd love to you're it's true
inspiration and the the wealth of
knowledge is just unbelievable so thank
you again for giving me three hours
which has felt like 15 minutes my final
question is a tongue in cheek one but
you've got it I'm giving you three
phenomenologists and you have to choose
one uh hle Merlo Ponte wow uh well I'm
going to go for Merlo Ponte because he's
like a a combination of H and
haiger both of them yeah okay and he's
French
so back your your your Franco File
comment earlier on that everything from
France is wonderful including French
philosophy so apart when it Reigns in
June according to my
model who's French rather than german
yes yeah absolutely uh and a bit more
legible of course but the style is just
so much more pleasurable to engage with
of his writing than heidig has his own
style but it's uh it's much harder and H
is he's a mathematician
so there's few hyphens in Merlo Ponte
despite the hyphen in the name the
H yes Julian thank you so much um I
think we probably there's been a couple
of WiFi on and off but this is the
beauty of editing as I will go in and
scrub it all out but um great genuinely
on my part it's been an absolute
pleasure um I know Daniel on the rest of
the inference rest clear enough you're
able to follow it all make a story out
of it I hope so uh but yes for me and
the rest of the team here at the
Institute thank you so much my pleasure
yeah